<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Rich Games</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2022-04-30T20:31:51-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Liz Lam</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Some Quick Thoughts on Simple Chess Variants by G.P. Jelliss</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/30/simple-chess-variants/"/>
   <updated>2022-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/30/simple-chess-variants</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Simple Chess Variants by G.P. Jelliss is a densely packed booklet that describes many 
chess variants in just 14 short pages.  It is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayhematics.com/v/simplevariants.pdf&quot;&gt;available to read&lt;/a&gt; on his website in PDF format.  The booklet feels almost like an academic paper where Jelliss covers many topics of “simple” variants.  He is quite restrictive on what is considered a “chess variant”, so you won’t find varieties that fall too far away from the chess game we all know and love.  This sentiment is best described by a quote from the booklet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In most of the variants selected here the aim is checkmate of a royal piece. In my view it is questionable whether games with other objectives are chess at all! Games for more than two players, or on special boards, or requiring other equipment are mostly excluded, as are variants that appear to me to be entirely arbitrary.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways, I appreciate this boundary since I’ve see many games as “chess like” or a “chess variant” that doesn’t feel like chess to me at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also found the content interesting for a different reason.  I’ve been experimenting with designing abstract games.  This is a little treasure trove of different types of moves and rules (albeit in a chess context) that 
is great for considering game design in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a quick introduction to different types of “simple” chess variants, give the booklet a read.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Many Chess Tutorials with Triple S Games</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/20/triple-s-games/"/>
   <updated>2022-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/20/triple-s-games</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that I LOVE chess variants.  So I was pleasantly surprised to 
discover the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC5--Olk4nljSNeT5wXfTOuA&quot;&gt;Triple S Games YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; where there are many succinct
tutorials on exactly that.  The channel is not exclusive to chess variants, but has
many abstract tutorials as well.  The videos are short and sweet and high quality.
Here is a sample of some that caught my eye:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Uy3rp20db4M&quot;&gt;Puzzle Board Chess&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/watch?v=VavTU_UEg7o&quot;&gt;Los Alamos Chess&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4lPMrFtd0PA&quot;&gt;Chess Unbound&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TvA9mAOpqW0&quot;&gt;Janus Chess&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5JxTU_KqdGo&quot;&gt;Diplomat Chess&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=snmEj7Xve_U&quot;&gt;Glinski’s Hexagonal Chess&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NuzgnSQVKGU&quot;&gt;Infinite Chess&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Triple S Games also has many &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/designers/jim&quot;&gt;custom components on The Game Crafter&lt;/a&gt;.  For
those of you who don’t have the exotic board sizes or pieces needed to play some
of these variants, check it out!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Abstract Tutorials and Reviews with The Boardgame Kaptain</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/09/boardgame-kaptain/"/>
   <updated>2022-01-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/09/boardgame-kaptain</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is easy to get lost in the ever expanding sea of channels on YouTube.  With the explosion of game tutorials and reviews, everyone is vying for clicks and views.  But one in particular I wanted to bring attention to is the The Boardgame Kaptain.  Although it is not solely for abstract or historical games, I am surprised by the amount of abstract games this channel contains.  I did a quick peruse of the uploaded videos and thought I’d share a list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x94mjlEmEDA&quot;&gt;NXS Ragnarok&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oi5yYWuOqt4&quot;&gt;Quantum&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eDGei98yBtY&quot;&gt;Game of Y&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=prSdnrdO1Nw&quot;&gt;Batalo&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fO5GCfGUrI4&quot;&gt;Mijnlieff&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2ImNafdiohA&quot;&gt;Mijnlieff Modular Board Expansion&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nv2AzUuV1pA&quot;&gt;Hexentafl&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5dh8akYYMAM&quot;&gt;Paco Sako&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F0w8a8XMs2E&quot;&gt;Raft &amp;amp; Scupper&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VpFS_P56oEE&quot;&gt;Sovereign Chess&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uOABbW2LnmY&quot;&gt;Saiju&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bwPPvpM7jEA&quot;&gt;Flink&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_KqwV-Bbuv8&quot;&gt;Onager&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y3cPdn0bd7k&quot;&gt;Niju&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OmAbnuPm4FI&quot;&gt;KuniUmi&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CfANrXAYet4&quot;&gt;Green Skull&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jrkj-1GE42s&quot;&gt;Return to Camelot&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ri_s00odGSk&quot;&gt;Shobu&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=euoMn25UJOs&quot;&gt;Royal Game of Ur&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an exhaustive list of the abstracts on their channel but it’s already an impressive one!
It’s obvious to me that The Boardgame Kaptain likes to highlight small indie developers of abstract games and everyone who is interested should go check out his channel!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Mini Xiang Qi</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/mini-xiangqi/"/>
   <updated>2021-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/28/mini-xiangqi</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mini Xiang Qi is a smaller variation of Xiang Qi (or Chinese Chess) played on a 7x7 board.  Its design is credited to Shigenobu Kusumoto (1974).  Each player starts off with 12 pieces each: 1 General, 2 Horses, 2 Cannons, 2 Chariots and 5 Soldiers (see initial setup below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mini-xiangqi-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mini Xiang Qi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no Advisors, Elephants or river in this abridged version of the game.  Most of the rules are the same with the exception that a soldier can move forward, left and right from the beginning of the game as though it has already crossed the river.  In Mini Xiang Qi there is no river on the board and a player wins by checkmating the opposing side’s general.  Here’s a refresher on how the relevant pieces move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Moves 1 step vertically or horizontally but not diagonally.  &lt;br /&gt;
Generals must stay in their castle&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Horse&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
May move 1 step vertically or horizontally and then 1 step diagonally. 
It can not move if there is any piece blocking the path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cannon&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
Moves like a rook but in order to capture must jump over exact one piece horizontally or vertically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chariot&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
Moves like a rook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soldier&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
Moves and captures by moving one step forward and one step horizontally.
Soldiers can also be promoted (optional) to a Chariot, Cannon or Horse after reaching the last 2 opposite ranks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Some Quick Thoughts on Understanding the Elephant: Part 1</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/10/understanding-the-elephant/"/>
   <updated>2021-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/10/understanding-the-elephant</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/understanding-elephant-part1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Understanding the Elephant Part 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/32314657-understanding-the-elephant&quot;&gt;Understanding the Elephant: A Xiangqi Primer Part 1: History of Xiangqi&lt;/a&gt; written by
Jim Png is one of the many books on Xiangqi (Chinese Chess) from this prolific author.
He is also the creator and maintainer of xqinenglish.com, a site dedicated to the game.
Just after a few paragraphs into the book, you can really get a sense of the passion and
dedication he has for Xiangqi.  The book itself is split up into 3 sections: history, famous
players and folk lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and very dense portion of the book is meant to present evidence of the possible Chinese
origin of chess.  It is a popular belief that chess came from India due to H.J.R. Murray’s ideas presented 
in his canonical book, The History of Chess.  Png challenges some of these ideas due to the fact that 
Murray studied Arabic and was able to research Arabic sources in great detail.  He also mentions an absence of research of Chinese literature due to Murray’s own lack of knowledge of Chinese.  It is definitely an interesting point.  Png continues by presenting a ton of references of ancient Chinese poems and literature as well as taking a closer look at the kanji characters that are on Xiangqi pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second section of the book tells many tales of famous Xiangqi players.  Although some of the stories were interesting, to be honest I mostly skimmed through this part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last and final section tells some of the folk lore and myths surrounding Xiangqi.  This doesn’t really present necessarily evidence about the origin story, but does indicate that Xiangqi has been around long enough to have myths and folklore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this was a fun book to go through.  It’s a bit of a misnomer to call it a “primer” since it doesn’t really even tell how to play the game.  This series of books is certainly a labor of love and Png believes that anyone that loves a subject enough would want to know more about its history.  The result is this part 1 of the “primer” series.  In my opinion, this book is solidly in the “for chess history buffs” category and I would recommend it to anyone who is interested in seeing the chess origin story from a different point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Photoblog: Making a Pai Sho Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/18/making-a-paisho-board/"/>
   <updated>2021-06-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/18/making-a-paisho-board</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re a fan of Avatar: The Last Airbender, you will probably be familiar with Pai Sho.  It’s a fictional game that constantly makes an appearance in this animated series.  Although there are no official rules for Pai Sho, there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://skudpaisho.com/site/games/&quot;&gt;many community driven ones&lt;/a&gt;.  I recently picked up this extra small &lt;a href=&quot;https://baronalbatross.company.site/products/Pai-Sho-XXS-Game-Kit-p354041377&quot;&gt;DIY Pai Sho kit&lt;/a&gt;.  The kit contains all the pieces needed to assembly a board.  The tiles (tokens) included are for one of the more popular fan made games called “Skud Pai Sho”.  Putting it together wasn’t too difficult, but a utility knife is definitely needed to cut out all the board parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-paisho-kit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Pai Sho Kit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I glued the board together, I decided to wood burn the sections.  In Pai Sho, the sections are called “gardens”.  Unfortunately, I got glue all over the board.  In addition, I was off a little bit so there were some gaps in the middle as a result.  If you decide to try this kit, definitely take the time to measure everything out on this step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-paisho-in-progress.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Pai Sho Kit&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-paisho-in-progress2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Pai Sho Kit&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-paisho-burning-done.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Pai Sho Kit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the pieces, I used coffee to stain them and then put a layer of Mod Podge Dimensional
Magic on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-paisho-pieces.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Pai Sho Kit&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-paisho-pieces-upclose.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Pai Sho Kit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if I would recommend using the Mod Podge Dimensional Magic because some of the coats came out cloudy.  I don’t know if I just put on too much or if that is just the nature of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-paisho-done.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DIY Pai Sho Kit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, I was still quite pleased with how everything turned out.  This is a tiny board to play on which makes it’s idea for taking on the go.  The compact size also makes it a low time investment as DIY projects go.  Now it’s time for a cup of tea and a game of Pai Sho.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Photoblog: Coloring a Brandub Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/20/coloring-brandub/"/>
   <updated>2021-05-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/20/coloring-brandub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I made a Brandub board and I wanted to experiment with some color.
I have used tea and coffee stains in the past, but I wanted to try something different this time.  I had a box
of Prismacolor Premier (erasable) pencils and I was pleasantly surprised how well they worked.
I started with the corner squares using the color “Terra Cotta” and “Light Green” for the Magpie markings (as well the decorations on the border).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coloring-brandub1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coloring a Brandub Board 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coloring-brandub2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coloring a Brandub Board 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that gently using the eraser (these are after all erasable colored pencil) helped blend in the colors into the wood.  I finished the border with a “Light Brown” and colored the 4 center defender spots with a combination of “Light Green” and “Light Brown”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coloring-brandub3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coloring a Brandub Board 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coloring-brandub4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coloring a Brandub Board 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last step was to add a coat of sanding sealant and I was impressed how that toned everything down and really brought everything together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coloring-brandub5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coloring a Brandub Board 5&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/coloring-brandub6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Coloring a Brandub Board 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun with this board and see more colored boards in my future.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Print On Demand Gems</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/30/pod-gems/"/>
   <updated>2021-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/30/pod-gems</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Print on demand games can get a bad rap.  I think this is mostly because anyone with an idea can publish a game regardless if it’s been vetted or not.  This is not necessarily a bad thing.  It gives opportunity to those who may not have another avenue for bringing their games to life.  In the age of self-published content, there is a lot that needs to be filtered.  Here is a couple of print on demand games from several print companies that I think are worth taking a look at (though not all of them are abstract strategy games).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Print and Play Games&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.printplaygames.com/product/niju/&quot;&gt;Ni-Ju&lt;/a&gt; by Néstor Romeral Andrés  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.printplaygames.com/product/blue/&quot;&gt;Blue&lt;/a&gt; by Néstor Romeral Andrés&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Game Crafter&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/four-tribes&quot;&gt;Four Tribes&lt;/a&gt; by Grey Gnome Games  &lt;br /&gt;
Memory Kings by &lt;a href=&quot;https://sneakypirates.itch.io/memory-kings&quot;&gt;Sneaky Pirate Games&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/the-garden-gate-pai-sho-set&quot;&gt;Pai Sho&lt;/a&gt; by The Garden Gate  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/camelot&quot;&gt;Camelot&lt;/a&gt; by Parker Brothers  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/cam&quot;&gt;Cam&lt;/a&gt; by Parker Brothers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drive Thru Cards&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivethrucards.com/product/172034/Pairs-Tree-Deck&quot;&gt;Pairs&lt;/a&gt;: Tree Deck by Cheapass Games  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivethrucards.com/product/111130/Light-Speed&quot;&gt;Light Speed&lt;/a&gt; by Cheapass Games&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a favorite print on demand game or company? 
Tweet us &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/richfamilygames&quot;&gt;@richfamilygames&lt;/a&gt; and share them!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of Hnefatafl by Pub Games of England</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/28/hneftafl-pub-games-england/"/>
   <updated>2021-03-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/28/hneftafl-pub-games-england</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hneftafl…the vikings’ board game by Pub Games of England is an interesting vintage set.  There are no dates on the box.  If I had to guess, I would say it was produced some time in the 1980’s.   I’ve seen the set for sale online with a slightly different box label stating the company was located in Sussex, England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This set is simple and beautiful.  The rustic wooden board is compact measuring at 5.5 inches squared.  It is a 7x7 playing area with holes instead of squares.  The playing pieces are wooden pegs that fit into the holes.  There are 12 light wood attackers, 6 dark wood defenders and 1 king.  If you’re thinking this seems unusual for a brandub sized board, you’re right!  There are 50% more pieces than your classic brandub game.  Also unusual is the setup of the game (shown in the picture).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hnefatafl-pub-games-of-england.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hnefatafl by Pub Games of England&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules will feel very normal for any fan of tafl games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers move first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king may enter the center square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All pieces move like a rook in chess.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces captured by sandwiching.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The defenders win by the king escaping to any edge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The attackers win by capturing the king on 4 sides.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The king can be captured on 3 sides if it sitting on a space orthogonal to the center square.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great little set that is sometimes hard to find.  I do feel there are probably too many pieces for the board size (though it’s not as bad as the game of ard ri).  The pegs and compact form factor makes it perfect to play at a coffee shop or travelling.  I wish I knew more about the publishers.  The fun part for me when finding these old vintage sets is not only the variation in rules but learning a bit about the publishers that produced them.  If you happen to know more, feel free to DM or tweet to @richfamilygames.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mini Tori Shogi</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/27/mini-tori-shogi/"/>
   <updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/27/mini-tori-shogi</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a big fan of small Shogi games such as Mini Shogi.  Tori Shogi (also known as Bird Shogi) is considered to be the smallest of the historic variants.  It is played on a 7x7 grid with 16 pieces per player.  With a total
of 32 pieces and just 49 squares, the game can feel a little cramped.  As a result, I have been wanting to experiment with a smaller version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same vein as Mini Shogi, I came up with a smaller Tori Shogi game that I not so cleverly
call Mini Tori Shogi.  It is played on a 5x5 board and each player has 6 pieces.  The pieces are
traditional pieces from the original Tori Shogi game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each player has 2 Pheasants, 2 Cranes, 1 Phoenix, and 1 Falcon.  &lt;br /&gt;
The board is arranged like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mini-tori-shogi-setup.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mini Tori Shogi Setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pheasants moves forward to the 2nd space and diagonally back 1 space (left or right).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Cranes move 1 space any direction except horizontally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Phoenix moves 1 space any direction.  This is the King/General piece.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Falcon moves 1 space any direction except backwards and promotes to an Eagle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Eagle can:  &lt;br /&gt;
 a.) Move 1 space forward, left, right and back diagonally.  &lt;br /&gt;
 b.) Move 2 spaces back diagonally.  &lt;br /&gt;
 c.) Move as many spaces forward diagonally and back vertically (no jumping allowed).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the Falcon promotes when it reaches the last row of the opposing side.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Captured pieces are allowed to be dropped back on the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first person who captures their opponent’s Phoenix wins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The set itself was fun to make.  The board is a 1/4 inch red oak plywood containing a grid burned in with a Razortip wood burner.  I was originally going to make the pieces with the original Kanji characters and helper markers that indicate how to move.  I love how Kanji characters look, but decided to explore the use of bird silhouettes.  They are not perfect, but I liked how they turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/mini-tori-shogi-homemade.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Mini Tori Shogi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, after playing a few game, I think I need to iterate more on which pieces to use and the setup. 
Although I enjoy the aesthetics of the game, there are some problems with the gameplay.  For example, at the start of the game, the Pheasants can only move forward to the second space.  That means 2 of the 3 moves it can make are not possible.  Also, the lack of long distance moving pieces (like a Rook or Bishop) makes the game less dynamic and bit slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was still a fun experiment and I will probably continue to iterate on it.  Please feel free to give any feedback or ideas by tweeting to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/richfamilygames&quot;&gt;@richfamilygames&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of Swords & Shields</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/23/swords-and-shields/"/>
   <updated>2020-12-23T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/23/swords-and-shields</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Shields by Milton Bradley (USA) is another vintage find of a classic Tafl game. Published in 1970, it embraces the Norse tradition with decorative Viking themed graphics. The game give credit to its history with the following in the inside cover of the box:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/swords-and-shields-inside-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Swords and Shields inside cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The components are pretty nice. The game board folds out to a large playing area and is made of a thick high quality cardboard similar to Monopoly or Sorry. The pieces are made of a light molded plastic with attractive details. My only complaint is they are little too light. I found myself accidentally knocking them over more times than I would expect. There are 16 attacking sword pieces, 8 defending shield pieces and a Chief Shield that acts as the King piece. The pieces are played on the intersection of lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/swords-and-shields-pieces.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Swords and Shields pieces&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/swords-and-shields-pieces-upclose.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Swords and Shields pieces upclose&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/swords-and-shields-complete.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Swords and Shields setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rules for gameplay are very similar to the historical Tablut.
Swords (attackers) move first.
All pieces move orthogonally (like a Rook in Chess).
Capturing pieces are done by sandwiching an opponent’s piece.
A piece may safely move in between 2 opponent pieces without being captured.
The Chief Shield is allowed to participate in captures.
The Chief Shield is generally captured on 2 sides, unless sitting on center dot where it requires a capture on 4 sides.
Swords win by capturing the Chief Shield.
Shields win when Chief Shield escapes to an edge.
There are however some small differences in the details:
The Chief Shield can move back into the center dot after leaving it.
Only the Chief Shield can move through the dot.
If the Chief Shield is on a dot that is adjacent to the center, it can be captured with just one Sword,
sandwiching the Chief Shield with the center dot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/swords-and-shields-diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Swords and Shields diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is nowhere in the rules that suggest you can capture other pieces in this manner, so I assume this is a special capture case for the Chief Shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Shields is a great commercial example of a published Tafl game. It has pretty much kept most of the traditional rules in place with small variations. I like that the Chief Shield is most vulnerable right outside of the center dot. It forces the defending player to move its Chief quickly out of the center area where it may normally just sit for a while. It is also easy to pick up a used copy on a marketplace platform like eBay for anyone who wants to add it to their own collection.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My Top Threes</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/my-top-threes/"/>
   <updated>2020-11-23T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/23/my-top-threes</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about my favourite games and what my “Top Ten” list would look like.
Spoiler Alert: I couldn’t come up with the list because there are so many games I like for
different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided to came up with a “Top Threes” list in different categories. Some categories are simply games produced by some of my favourite independent game publishers, others are just games I like to play with my kids. Not all are purely abstract strategy games, but many are. I hope you reading the list as much a I enjoyed putting it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hnefatafl Variants&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandub (7x7)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tablut (9x9)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fetlar Hnefatafl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Historic/Ancient (not Hnefatafl)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Backgammon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Royal Game of Ur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kid Friendly&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JamSumo by Cubiko Games&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hippos and Crocodiles by Nestorgames&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice Dice by Looney Labs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chess Variants (regional and/or modern)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Xiang Qi (Chinese Chess)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plunder Chess&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makruk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logy Games&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Safari-Dual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most Honest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chameleon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nestorgames&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleepers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tetrarchia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Garden of Mars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vintage 3M Bookshelf Games&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Break Thru&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Twixt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feudal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Abstract (after 1900’s)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tak&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Camelot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Interview With Hnefatafl Books Author Damian Walker</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/23/damian-walker-interview/"/>
   <updated>2020-10-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/23/damian-walker-interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a part of an ongoing interview series with book authors who write about our favorite types of games. Damian Walker is the author of not one but two books on hnefatafl.  Both &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lulu.com/shop/damian-gareth-walker/an-introduction-to-hnefatafl/paperback/product-22385082.html&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Hneftafl&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lulu.com/shop/damian-walker/reconstructing-hnefatafl/hardcover/product-21428427.html&quot;&gt;Reconstructing Hnefatafl&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to this Norse game and I’ve been a huge fan ever since.  I am delighted to share this interview with Damian everyone and hope you enjoy it too.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you tell us a little about yourself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a web developer living in Yorkshire, England. I’m from these parts, although I’ve also lived in Northwest England and, when I was very young, in New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you first learn about hnefatafl?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was in a book I got from the library back in 2002: Jack Botermans’ “The World of Games”. I was between jobs at the time, and I was very much attracted to these games that could be easily made with things lying about the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What drew you in about it compared to other ancient board games?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attractive rotational symmetry drew my attention, as well as the asymmetrical division of the pieces between the two teams. Though it wasn’t the only game from that book that attracted my attention. What drew me further in was the air of mystery, the fact that at the time we didn’t really know how it was played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What inspired you to write not just one book, but two books about hnefatafl?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two books are really aimed at different readerships. The first one (Reconstructing Hnefatafl) is the more serious one of the two, aimed at re-enactors and other people who want to bring the game to modern audiences; it goes into a lot of detail about historical evidence and game balance in order to justify its reconstructions. The newer book (An Introduction to Hnefatafl) is more of a light read for people who just want to find out a bit more about the game and to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you ever considered combining both books into one?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes and no. I’d actually thought about writing a larger book on the game, having gathered enough research to fill one. But my day job can be quite demanding of my energy, so that project has been pushed back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How long did it take to write the books?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to tell how long Reconstructing Hnefatafl took, as it was done in a few stages across a number of years. It drew on a never-published book I’d been working on since about 2004, so it includes about ten years of research. An Introduction to Hnefatafl was originally a 20-page booklet, which took me a week to put together from the same research. I used to sell that from my web site. I then reworked it into the book as it exists now, which probably took me a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you feel when you first published it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very pleased with Reconstructing Hnefatafl. It was originally going to be a free PDF. I got a lot of support from David Parlett, author of the Oxford Book of Board Games, and through him from Irving Finkel of the British Museum. They suggested I present it as a paper at the Board Games Colloquium that’s held each year. That never happened, as I couldn’t afford to travel, but I was glad to share it instead as a printed book. I was quite proud of it as it was the first book on the game that made it in print.
An Introduction to Hnefatafl was also quite fun, although since it was the second book I published, the experience had fewer surprises for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was the hardest chapters to write?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly can’t remember, although it’s probably the Alea Evangelii chapter of Reconstructing Hnefatafl. It was nigh on impossible to get anyone to play that thing with me, especially as the rules were experimental. It was only some years afterwards that the game got extensively playtested. That showed that my reconstruction is far from balanced, and a lot more research on that game is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there plans for more books or updates to the current ones?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I should revisit Reconstructing Hnefatafl, as the research is falling out of date - particularly on things like game balance, where there are many more willing play-testers now than there were when I wrote it. There’s that larger book on the game that I mentioned, which I’m not actively working on but I haven’t abandoned either. I’d also like to write more books following the format of “A Book of Historic Board Games”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alea Evangelii is a tafl game that is played on a 19x19 grid.  Do you think there is a connection here to the game of Go?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there’s a connection. In fact there are three games I know of played on a similar looking board. There’s alea evangelii, go, and an unknown game which appears to be a large form of ludus latrunculorum. I think the board size in all these cases is just coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You also wrote, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/damian-gareth-walker/a-book-of-historic-board-games/paperback/product-1re9pzq4.html&quot;&gt;A Book of Historic Board Games&lt;/a&gt;.  Can you talk a bit about the journey and inspiration behind this book?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my favourite of the three books I’ve written, although it’s also the least successful. I’m interested in ancient board games in general, and I wanted to write something that drew on my research beyond hnefatafl. There are already many books that cover large numbers of games, so I decided to select just twelve and cover them in a reasonable amount of detail. It was inspired more by books like David Pritchard’s Brain Games than by the books that attempt to cover as many games as possible.
This was the most fun to write, and led me into some very interesting research. This kind of project is much easier now than it was even ten years ago; the vast number of digitised documents means that one can go back to primary sources without having to leave the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Many consider you an authoritative source on hnefatafl.  How does that make you feel?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like quite a responsibility for someone who hasn’t really been that active over the past few years! I’m glad that interest in the game has increased as time has drawn on, though, and I hope to have the time in future to bring myself up to date with new developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How many hnefatafl sets do you own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I might have about twenty by now. I spent quite a long time looking for attractive sets on eBay, and I also kept one of nearly every design of board that I made myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have a favorite set?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems a bit conceited, but I do like the 9x9 set that I used to make, with the walnut veneer edge. Of the more well-known ones that people might recognise, I really like the wooden one that was marketed by York Archaeological Trust back in 1980, which you still see surfacing on eBay from time to time. It comes with a nice set of rules, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite historic hnefatafl variant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tablut is my favourite, as it’s the one we can be most certain about. I also think the 9x9 size makes for a good game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite modern variant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much like Sea Battle Tafl. It’s very elegant and easy to teach. Since I’m oriented more towards historic games, I like the fact that it manages balance without introducing too many imaginative new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often do you play now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly I very rarely get to play now. I was never a strong player, but I’m very out of practice now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you ever experimented with creating your own tafl variation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, I tend to prefer to uncover historical games than to create new ones. I have had a lot of fun pasting themes onto existing hnefatafl rules, though. I’m particularly fond of the Christmas one, with Santa and his eight elves trying to set off from the North Pole before sixteen naughty children ambush them and steal the presents!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks Damian for your time.  What is the best way for people to contact your or get in touch with you if they have more questions or just want to chat?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m quite active on Twitter nowadays, especially on my personal account (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cyningstan&quot;&gt;@cyningstan&lt;/a&gt;) so people are welcome to contact me there.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of Break Away</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/09/break-away-review/"/>
   <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/09/break-away-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Break Away: The game of confrontation and escape&lt;/em&gt; is a modern game that is unabashedly derived from our favorite Norse game, Hnefatafl.  It was originally a part of the Hi-Q Collection by CBS Toys, a division of CBS Inc.  Published in the early 1980’s, it is another example of how ancient games can evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The components are pretty simple.  The game consists of a blue plastic board with a 9x9 grid.  Each cell contains a hole that fits the plastic peg pieces.  There are 16 white pegs (though you won’t need them all in the base game), 8 blue pegs and 1 blue king (which is just another blue peg that is slightly larger).  At the ends of the board, the top lid comes off to reveal a compartment where the pieces can be comfortably stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/breakaway-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Break Away 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/breakaway-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Break Away 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Break Away contains most of the framework you would expect in a Tafl game. There are attackers and defenders (simply called white and blue pawns) that move like a rook in chess.  Capturing is done by sandwich ing a piece. The king is captured on all 4 sides and can itself participate in captures.
There is also nothing particularly special about the central square.  You can move through it and land on it like any other square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the rules start to break away (no pun intended) is in the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The king can only move 1 space at a time orthogonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defenders (blue) wins by escaping to the top or bottom edge of the board (where the compartments are).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can be captured in the corners, if the opposing pieces occupy both orthogonal cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/breakaway-corner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Break Away Corner Capture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a piece moves between two opposing pieces against the edge, a 3rd piece can capture it by surrounding it.  This is much like the modern shield wall rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/breakaway-edge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Break Away Edge Capture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The standard setup only allows for 12 white attackers as oppose to the usual 16.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/breakaway-setup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Break Away Setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned earlier, there are in fact 16 attackers included with the game.  The rules offer a “Master Break Away” variant that has a standard Tablut setup.  The rest of the rules are the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I mostly like this game.  I’m not as fond as variants that only allow the king to move 1 step at a time.  I know Magpie (which is a modern Brandub variation) has this same restriction, but I think it works better on the smaller 7x7 board.  The two edge escape and corner capture rules are different enough to give some nice variety.  All in all, it is still a welcomed addition to my Hnefatafl collection.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Making Dice</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/15/making-dice/"/>
   <updated>2020-08-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/15/making-dice</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t surprise anyone too much that gamers love dice.  The idea of some sort of randomizer have been around a long time with some ancient dice said to be dated as far back as 2500 BC. I’ve been experimenting with making dice and thought I’d jot down some of my techniques for those who are interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you need when making dice is wooden cubes.  You can buy these of various size at almost any hobby shop.  Using my wood burner, I burn the appropriate number of pips on each side.  I’ve played around with staining the die using coffee and wine.  What??!  Yes, coffee and/or wine.  Unfortunately known for staining clothes, carpet, and teeth, both coffee and wine acts as a great subtle stainer for light woods.  I usually stain the dice with few a few layers until I achieve the tint I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/making-dice1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;making dice 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like hard edges, you can pretty much stop at this point, but I like to sand the edges to reveal the original lighter wood color.  This lighter contrast accents the dice visually and gives it a nice round feeling in your hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/making-dice2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;making dice 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last step is to finish it off with a little coconut oil or beeswax.  Coconut oil will darken the wood a bit more than beeswax but both work pretty well.  Have you tried making your own dice?  Do you have a technique or oil that you like using?  Feel free to tweet me &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/richfamilygames&quot;&gt;@richfamilygames&lt;/a&gt; with your input.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Postcard Challenge</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08/14/postcard-challenge/"/>
   <updated>2020-08-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/14/postcard-challenge</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I created a side project for myself to design some micro games.  I randomly drew 7 boards on postcards with the intention of designing a game for each one over 7 days.  It doesn’t necessarily have to be one a day, but it’s a good starting point. Having the framework keeps me encouraged.  I don’t necessarily have high expectations of the games and think of them more as first drafts.  The exercise is also a way for me to overcome my shyness of just pulling the trigger on these things.  It’s true when they say, perfection is the enemy of done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/postcard-challenge-in-progress.png&quot; alt=&quot;postcard challenge progress&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also built a &lt;a href=&quot;https://postcard-challenge.vercel.app/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; to encourage anyone else if interested.  In the website, I describe a process where you can share your games (or the progress of your game design) on social media.  I drew this inspiration from the Inktober challenge.  I hope you able to give it a try and have a little fun in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Making A Chaturaji Set</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/14/chaturaji/"/>
   <updated>2020-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/14/chaturaji</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Chaturaji literally means “4 Kings”.  It is a 4 handed Indian chess variant with written sources dating back to 1030 A.D.  Like many of the ancient chess variants, sets can be hard to find.  In true maker fashion, I found some STL’s of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinshape.com/items/8681-3d-printed-nishapur-chess&quot;&gt;Nishapur Chess pieces&lt;/a&gt; and had a friend 3D print them for me.  The King and Queen pieces look similar enough where you can make the 4 sets of pieces needed for Chaturaji.  With the help of my 3 and 5 year old daughters, we painted the pieces different colors.  Painting chess pieces with children is….interesting.  Let’s just say many layers of colors (including some very muddy ones) were involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board is an 8x8 inch red oak plywood which was originally the start for another game.  I played around with the grid and it ended up with this imprecise and rustic look.  In the end, I felt like the set came together and it was a fun way to spend some time with my kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chaturaji-in-progress.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chaturaji in progress&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chaturaji-white-closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chaturaji white closeup&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chaturaji-white-gold-closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chaturaji white and gold closeup&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chaturaji-all-4-closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chaturaji all 4 closeup&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chaturaji-done.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chaturaji done&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Angel Chess Microsite</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/14/angel-chess-site/"/>
   <updated>2020-06-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/14/angel-chess-site</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across a chess variant called &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/153759/angel-chess&quot;&gt;Angel Chess on the BoardGameGeek website&lt;/a&gt;. 
What drew me in was the image of an old patent containing a beautiful hand drawn diagram of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was immediately intrigued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://angel-chess-project.now.sh/&quot;&gt;microsite on Angel Chess&lt;/a&gt;.  It’s still a work in progress but feel free to explore it and learn about this very interesting game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/angel-chess-site.png&quot; alt=&quot;angel-chess-site&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Pex</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/10/how-to-play-pex/"/>
   <updated>2020-06-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/10/how-to-play-pex</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My 5 year daughter sporadically designed her first board game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pex.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pex&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually not a bad game and fun to play with children.    &lt;br /&gt;
I thought it be fun to share her rules and see what people thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SETUP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start off with a 6x5 board with the long side facing each player.      &lt;br /&gt;
Place 6 pieces of your color on the first row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RULES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take turns doing the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roll a dice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move your piece the exact number of spaces as the dice value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are allowed to move your piece in any direction (both orthogonally and diagonally).  &lt;br /&gt;
You are not allowed to move into the same space twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WIN CONDITION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move all your pieces into the opposite side of the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
You also win if the opposing player can not move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give it a try and feel free to let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>44 Etsy Sales</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/05/31/etsy-sales/"/>
   <updated>2020-05-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/31/etsy-sales</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rich Games is not only a hobby site, but it is also hobby business.  I haven’t focused on it as much lately, but I enjoy making board games via pyrography (wood burning) and have sold 44 sets to date on Etsy.   I definitely don’t make a profit on these games (especially if you consider my labor), but I enjoy the creative process.  It’s fun to look back on the sets and I’d thought I share the numbers on what games sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 Men’s Morris: 2  &lt;br /&gt;
5 Men’s Morris: 1  &lt;br /&gt;
9 Men’s Morris: 2  &lt;br /&gt;
Puluc: 2  &lt;br /&gt;
Yote: 1  &lt;br /&gt;
Pulijudam: 1  &lt;br /&gt;
Five Lines: 2  &lt;br /&gt;
French Military Game: 1  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Royal Game of Ur: 13&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
Fanorona: 2  &lt;br /&gt;
Senet: 1  &lt;br /&gt;
Seega: 2  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Hnefatafl/Brandub (7x7): 5&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Hnefatafl (9x9): 5&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Hnefatafl (11x11): 2&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
Shut the Box: 1  &lt;br /&gt;
Fox &amp;amp; Geese: 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Royal Game of Ur by far has been my best selling game with Hneftafl variants taking 2nd and 3rd place.  I attribute the success of the Royal Game of Ur with the play through that came out with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WZskjLq040I&quot;&gt;Tom Scott vs. Irving Finkel&lt;/a&gt; for International Tabletop Day in 2017.  It’s a great video and garnered a lot of attention for this ancient little gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hnefatafl games (all variants) make up 12 of the 44, which calculate to 27%. 
The Morris games (3, 5 &amp;amp; 9) make up 11% of total sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if these are really fair comparisons since I made varying amounts of each game but it’s interesting to see how all the numbers break down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/etsy_sold_page1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Etsy sold page 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/etsy_sold_page2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Etsy sold page 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Progressive Morris Games</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/04/24/progressive-morris/"/>
   <updated>2020-04-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/24/progressive-morris</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been pretty crazy in this post COVID-19 world.  I live in the San Francisco Bay Area and we’ve been sheltering in place for over a month now.  As I adjust to having the kids home due to school closures and still trying to work a full time job, there’s been little time for game &lt;em&gt;making&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there has been ample time for game &lt;em&gt;playing&lt;/em&gt; with the kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been spending a lot of afternoons in the front yard where there is a stone path to the gate.
One of the days, I decided to teach my 5 year old how to play some of the Morris games progressively.  Using chalk, I drew a 3 Men’s Morris board on one of the stones, then 5 Men’s Morris on the next one, and finally 9 Men’s Morris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played each game starting with the simplest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/prog_morris_game.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Front Yard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in the time of ancient days, the Morris games are a great way to pass the time.  The simple rules and setup make it easy to sketch out a board and play using found objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My daughter loved it and I imagine there will be more Morris games in our future.  In the midst of all the uncertainly, it’s nice to find the silver linings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Making a Noggin the Nog Dice Tower</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/noggin-dice-tower/"/>
   <updated>2020-02-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/noggin-dice-tower</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My latest completed project is a Noggin the Nog themed dice tower that I made for my daughter.  I didn’t actually make the box itself.  I bought the unstained and unfinished plywood dice tower on Etsy for $12 and over a period of 8 months started working on it a bit at a time.  I’m pretty pleased with the final product and my daughter was ecstatic to get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/noggin-dice-tower-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dice tower 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/noggin-dice-tower-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dice tower 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/noggin-dice-tower-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dice tower 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/noggin-dice-tower-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dice tower 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noggin the Nog was a popular British children’s book and TV series.  The TV series was originally broadcast in the late 1950’s and early 1960’s.  The show created by Oliver Postgate and Peter Firmin is based around the character Noggin and his entourage.  The characters are inspired by the Lewis Chessmen, which some have postulated could have been used to play the ancient Norse game, Hnefatafl.  There is even a book in the series called “The Game” in which Hnefatafl is a central theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a fun project work on and it’s nice to take the time to work on 1 piece.  I was thinking of making some Noggin themed dice, but I haven’t really figured out what that would look like.  If you have suggestions, feel free to tweet me at @richfamilygames on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Alea Evangelii by Forever Family Games</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/01/alea-evangelii-forever-family-games/"/>
   <updated>2020-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/01/alea-evangelii-forever-family-games</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Any serious Hnefatafl enthusiast will eventually find themselves reading about the largest known version.  Alea Evangelii, meaning “Game of the Gospels” is referenced in an medieval century manuscript.  The manuscript contains a beautiful diagram of this game on a massive 19x19 grid.  It is said to have been played during the time of King Athelstan of the English.  No game rules exists.  The text on this manuscript is all allegorical containing metaphors for the gospels. It is interesting to note that the 19x19 grid is also used in the Chinese game of Go and like Go, the pieces are also played on the intersection of lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is common to try to recreate this game on a Go board using the black and white pieces as attackers and defenders and perhaps a chess piece as the king.  Although Tafl sets in general are becoming more easy to purchase in general on sites like Etsy or eBay, Alea Evangelii sets are a bit more obscure and harder to come by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Family Forever Games version is one of the only sets I’ve found for sale that is easily accessible and isn’t an expensive custom request.  The components are simple but surprisingly well made.  The two part canvas board (each panel is 11x14 inches) is felted and comes together to create the playing area.  The playing board is a nice print on a sturdy stock paper and affixed onto the canvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/alea-felt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;felt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/alea-2-together.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;board together&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The king piece is a painted wooden pawn and colored glass gems (4 white, 20 red &amp;amp; 48 blue) make up the rest of the pieces.  The board clearly marks where to put the pieces for easy set up.  Everything comes nicely packed in a white cardboard box with branded stickers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/alea-board-with-pieces.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;full set&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/alea-box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;box&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board could use a couple tweaks to improve the gaming experience.  The grid lines are a little too thick and I find the high black and white contrast to be a little straining on my eyes.  I think this could be mitigated if the lines were about 1/2 its current width.  Also, although the blue and red place markers are great for quick set up, I find them a little distracting during game play.  I think it’s because they too closely resemble the actual glass gems and it would be nice it they were a little lighter in hue and color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The set also comes with a 7 page rule set.  The Forever Family Games version includes the use of “elite guards” which they call “bishops” represented by the white gems.  Elite guards are a somewhat modern invention but are commonly seen in Alea Evangelii rules.  The rule book also designates what I usually call “defenders” as “guards” and the “attackers” as “rebels”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming, the reader knows about the basics of common Tafl game play, the differentiating rules are listed here (of course the rule book contains every detail needed to play):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rebels start (this is actually pretty common)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the king is on the throne (center square), it requires a 4 sided capture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the king is next to the throne, it requires a 3 sided capture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is anywhere else on the board, it requires a 2 sided capture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the king leaves the throne, no one can occupy that square (including the king)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 4 adjacent guards to the king are the “bishops”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bishops can not be captured and can not assist in captures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;King wins by escaping to the edge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have interest in Alea Evangelii, this is probably the best and most reasonably priced option out there.
As of writing this article, Forever Family Games has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/shop/ForeverFamilyGames&quot;&gt;Etsy store&lt;/a&gt; that sells it for around $40 (includes shipping and handling).  I found that purchasing from their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.storenvy.com/stores/556398-forever-family-games&quot;&gt;Storenvy store&lt;/a&gt; was cheaper (about $32) even after the Storenvy fees and shipping to California.  Overall, I’ve been pretty happy with this set and enjoyed the games I’ve played so far.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of Thai Chess and Cambodian Chess by Gary Gifford</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/03/thai-chess-review/"/>
   <updated>2019-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/03/thai-chess-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/thai_chess_book.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2QIEnVx&quot;&gt;Thai Chess and Cambodian Chess: Makruk and Ouk Chattrangi&lt;/a&gt; is a self published book by Gary Gifford.  Those who love chess variants will appreciate this short read.  In just under 90 pages, Gifford gives an introduction to the history, rules, openings, recorded games and describes homemade sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gifford starts off with how he was personally introduced to Makruk when some friends invited him to play.  This peaked his interest and led him on a quest to find a book on this regional variant.  He even went as far as to contact a bookstore in Bangkok but with no success.  As the result of a seemingly lack of Makruk books in the world, he decided to write this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ouk Chattrang (the Cambodian version) is almost identical to Makruk. Both games appeared in the center of the former Khmer Empire (9th-15th A.D.).  The Khmer Empire included modern day Cambodia, Thailand, Laos, Vietnam, Myanmar and Malaysia.  Gifford gives a brief history, borrowing much of his information from H.R. Murray’s classic, History of Chess (1913).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the notable differences in Makruk is where the pawns are located.  Instead of the 2nd and 7th rank, the pawns sit on the 3rd and 6th rank.  Coincidentally (or maybe not), pawns do not move 2 spaces on their first moves and there is no en passant captures.  There is also no castling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another more subtle setup difference is Kings face the enemy Queens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/makruk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Makruk board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Makruk and Ouk Chattrang Setup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moves of most of the pieces will feel familiar with the exception of the Bishop and Queen.
These are much weaker pieces compared to those of Western chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Rook&lt;/strong&gt; moves the same as Western chess, any number of spaces in an orthogonal manner.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Horse&lt;/strong&gt; moves the same “L” shape move as the Western Knight.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Bishop&lt;/strong&gt; can only move 1 space diagonally or forward (not directly backwards or to the side).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;King&lt;/strong&gt; moves 1 space any direction as the Western King, but there is no castling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Queen&lt;/strong&gt; moves 1 space diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Pawns&lt;/strong&gt; move 1 space forward and capture 1 space diagonally as in Western Chess.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pawns promote on the 6th rank and only promote to Queens.  Which is unfortunate since the Queen
is almost the weakest piece on the board (second only to the pawns themselves).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special Ouk Chattrang Rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ouk Chattrang has a couple of special first moves that is not in Makruk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The King is allowed to move like a Horse on it’s first move, ending up on the 2nd rank.
The Queen is allowed to move forward 2 spaces on her first move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Counting Rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most unique things about Makruk that differentiates it from other regional chess variants is the counting rules.  Although, I have usually skipped these rules, Gifford emphasizes the importance of playing with them.  He compares playing Makruk without the counting rules is like playing Western chess without the castling rule or en passant captures.  This convinced me that in order to play an authentic version of a game, you can’t simply leave out rules that are not to your liking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The counting rules fall into 2 major categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Pawns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When all the pawns are captured or promoted (i.e. no one has pawns), the game must end in checkmate after 64 moves.
It is up the losing player to keep this count and you can end up with a draw instead of a lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bare King&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the losing player only has a King left on the board, look at the winning player’s pieces and this determines how many moves they have to checkmate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the winning player has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Rooks, then 8 minus total number of pieces on the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
1 Rook, then 16 minus total number of pieces on the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
2 Bishops, then 22 minus total number of pieces on the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
2 Horses, then 32 minus total number of pieces on the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
1 Bishop, then 44 minus total number of pieces on the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
1 Horse, then 64 minus total number of pieces on the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
Only Queens Left, then 64 minus total number of pieces on the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game can conceivable move from a No Pawns count to a Bare King count.
Once you are counting from the calculation made in the Bare King category, that’s it.
No recalculation is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I initially found this a bit confusing (which is why I have ignore the counting rules in the past).  Gifford seems to acknowledge this by providing counting exercises and answers in order for the new player to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Openings and Games&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next he categorizes and goes through a 16 different openings with names like “King Horse Low / Queen Horse High” and “Two Horse Low (Low Horse Constellation)”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a little video I made with &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2F30zUy&quot;&gt;my set&lt;/a&gt; to help further explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NRpwDSy04P0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As if to complement the 16 openings, Gifford then goes through 16 games, annotating and providing his insight every step of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Making Your Own Set&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last section is full of pictures and instructions on how to make your own sets.  This is covers everything from modifying &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ZCz4KZ&quot;&gt;cheap plastic&lt;/a&gt; sets to taking a trip to the hardware store to find nuts and bolts that would match.  Gifford insists on using pieces as traditional as possible.  Like the counting rules, there is an authenticity to it and it just wouldn’t quite be the same otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He states: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I will not play Makruk using a western set anymore than I would play a game of checkers using chess pieces.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something that rings true about that statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, if you have interest in Makruk or Ouk Chattrang, this is a great little book to get started with.  The author’s passion and expertise really comes through and it’s fun to share in some of that enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Drawing Fun with Inktober 2019</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/05/inktober-fun/"/>
   <updated>2019-11-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/05/inktober-fun</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://inktober.com/&quot;&gt;Inktober&lt;/a&gt; is an art challenge to produce an ink drawing every day for the month of October.  Every day has a word associated with it to draw inspiration from.  I had thought about participating last year but couldn’t quite find the time.  This year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/richfamilygames/status/1182135786046550016&quot;&gt;9 days into October&lt;/a&gt;, I decided it’s never too late to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some board game related drawings that I had some fun with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/inktober-day10-pattern.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inktober Day 10 Pattern&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/inktober-day11-snow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inktober Day 11 Snow&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/inktober-day21-treasure.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inktober Day 21 Treasure&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/inktober-day23-ancient.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inktober Day 23 Ancient&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/inktober-day26-dark.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inktober Day 26 Dark&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/inktober-day28-ride.png&quot; alt=&quot;Inktober Day 28 Ride&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Photoblog: Making a Hare & Hounds Set</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/01/photoblog-hare-hounds/"/>
   <updated>2019-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/01/photoblog-hare-hounds</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve made a Hare &amp;amp; Hounds (aka &lt;a href=&quot;https://richgames.xyz/2017/02/20/how-to-play-french-military-game/&quot;&gt;The French Military Game&lt;/a&gt;) set in the past.  It was pretty simple with just the lines.  Although that is perfectly sufficient to play this small but strategic game, I’ve been wanting to make a more creative version of it.  I also wanted to change my approach a bit on making board games.  Often times it takes me weeks or months to complete something.  This is mostly due to the fact that I have little kids and can only squeeze in a bit of time in the evenings.  So this time around, I treated this project more like a quick sketch or doodle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with a piece of red oak plywood and ruler, I drew in the actual grid/game area.  At this point, I wasn’t really sure what else I was going to do but just starting is half the battle.  After looking at a few random images on the internet of rabbits and dogs, I started sketching out the hare and hound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hare-hounds1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hare and hounds drawing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the sketches were done, the next step is to burn in the lines and drawings.  Red oak is really grainy and can be difficult to work with.  I’m still figuring out which is the best pyrography techniques to use with it.  In this case, I just worked in the shading as though I was doing a line drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hare-hounds2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hand and hound burned in and almost finished&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After filling in everything, the board still felt a bit off to me.  Adding some accents on the corners help balance out the art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hare-hounds3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hare and hounds complete&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this was done over a few nights, the actual art process happened pretty quickly.  I think it helps that the grid area is fairly simple and can be done quite easily.  This means I’m not laboring over large grids and burning a lot of squares.  This is probably not my favorite board, but it was a good “quick sketch” exercise.  I’m hoping to do more of these “quick sketches” to see what will come out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Interview with TAFL Author Jesse Robinson</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/01/jesse-robinson-interview/"/>
   <updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/09/01/jesse-robinson-interview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a part of an ongoing interview series with book authors who write about our favorite types of games.  Jesse Robinson is the author of TAFL, one of the first books on Hnefatafl.  Although the e-book was first self published in 2013, I only just recently had the pleasure of &lt;a href=&quot;https://richgames.xyz/2019/06/24/tafl-book.review/&quot;&gt;reading and reviewing it&lt;/a&gt;.  I’m excited to be able to share this interview with others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you tell us a little about yourself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born and raised in Massachusetts, but upon my son’s birth in 1990, we moved to Portland, Maine… and stayed there until 2005, when I moved to Japan. I have a “9-5’er” where I work in freezers at a food warehouse, but I’m also a maker of musical instruments - started way back when I was 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you first learn about hnefatafl?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I remember correctly, my 4th grade teacher, Mr. Dobbins, from Farnsworth Elementary School in Peabody, Mass. (which later became an old folks’ home), had gotten our class into trying out different board games from around the world, including such games as “Warlord”, from China (or… was it Mongolia? Hmmm… ), and Shogi, from Japan. Since then, I’d seen Hnefatafl boards while thumbing through a book or two in libraries, but didn’t really research it much until years later. Once I did, I was intrigued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What drew you in about it compared to other ancient board games?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it seemed at first glance to be set up a bit unfairly, as one side had nearly double the pieces of the other… until I tried playing, from one side, and then the other. The side with the lesser amount was in the middle of the board, and outnumbered by the other side, surrounding the first group. Something about the positioning in this way, seemed to help things even out as the game played out in its unfolding strategies. It was quite interesting in that it seemed to be a fairly good example of war being made upon an encampment by surprise attack of some marauding horde. lol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What inspired you to write a book about hnefatafl?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed not very well known out there, relatively… and I’m of both Native American (Siksika/Mohawk-Cree) and Norse descent - so I was attracted to the game as a part of the Nordic heritage. But I’d noticed that online, board game forum trolls would bicker and argue with each other about “the REAL AUTHENTIC rules”… when there really weren’t any, beyond the absolute basics. It seemed far more likely that, different camps, different kingdoms, different cabins and homes, different longboats… all had their specific preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How long did it take to write the book?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not really sure… I wanna say, less than a month, maybe? It wasn’t like a novel or anything… more like an introduction and list of rules/tutorial sort of thing, so it kind of wrote itself fairly quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you feel when you first published it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uhm, good, I think… pretty much not unlike getting something on my “to-do list” crossed off, at first - but when I started getting some nice reviews, it felt kinda kickass 😊&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was the hardest chapters to write?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm… maybe the introduction? I tried my darnedest to express my passion, but without rambling on and on… ahahahaha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You also wrote a book about Nine Men’s Morris, what was the inspiration behind that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fairly related, in that, the oldest known finding of an ancient Tafl board was found amid a shipwreck (if I remember correctly), but the interesting thing was that a Morris board was found on the reverse face of it, for a bit of alternate game play. Also, as the Tafl board had gone through many phases of evolution in size and rules as it went from kingdom to kingdom, so did Morris… and perhaps had become even more spread world-wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there plans for more books or updates to the current one?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had planned to do one on the many incarnations/rule-sets of Mancala, and also another on Egyptian Senet/Game of Ur. Not sure when I’ll finally get up off me arse and write them out, though… someday 😊&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How many hnefatafl sets do you own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to have a few I made, but now only one… but I plan to construct the largest one, Alea Evangelii, out of hardwoods sometime in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have a favorite set?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My present portable one - a buckskin pouch full of coloured glass “flat marbles” for the pieces, and when the pouch has its drawstring loosened, it lays flat… with a Tafl board inked on one side, and a Morris board on the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite historic hnefatafl variant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure… I suspect that once I make that BIG one, that will be my favourite - but the smaller sized board variants are wonderful for toting around in a pocket-sized build, or even with coins on a board face drawn on paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite modern variant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app on my phone. hahaha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often do you play now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it’s been many months - life things have been drastically taking my attention away. Changes in family (deaths, divorces, etc.) and my moving my workshop to a new location, bit by bit, has kept me busy - but I’m still a lover of the game. Plans for that big one I’d mentioned keep evolving in my mind 😊&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you ever experimented with creating your own tafl variation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas HAVE floated through my mind, yes… like a gi-hugic version of Alea Evangelii… perhaps with certain “hazzards” to avoid on the board, with some sort of penalties for landing in them… it’s a work in progress ^_~&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Photoblog: Making a Cam Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/29/photoblog-cam/"/>
   <updated>2019-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/29/photoblog-cam</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 1882, George S. Parker of Parker Brother started working on a game called &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/117864/chivalry&quot;&gt;Chivalry&lt;/a&gt;.  He wanted to create a game that was less complicated than chess but more interesting than checkers.  It was published in 1887 but did not really gain mainstream interest.  In 1930’s, the game was slightly modified, republished as Camelot and enjoyed it’s “golden age”.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/5251/camelot&quot;&gt;Camelot&lt;/a&gt; was said to be played by well known folks such as Jose Raul Capablanca and John F. Kennedy.  In 1949, a smaller version of Camelot called &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/117869/cam&quot;&gt;Cam&lt;/a&gt; was released.  The &lt;a href=&quot;https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/5251/camelot&quot;&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt; are pretty much the same as Camelot with some modification due to having a smaller board and less pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can easily find used versions of Camelot on eBay or etsy, but this is not so true for Cam.  Since I really enjoyed playing Camelot (having picked up a used copy in the past), I’d thought it be a fun project to make my own Cam board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start off by marking off the playing are and filling in the castle squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cam1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Starting a Cam board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continue to make progress and shade in every other square to give it a checkered look with the exception of the starting squares. Around this time I also decide to added some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan_Macdonald_of_Clanranald&quot;&gt;decorations inspired by the Clan Macdonald&lt;/a&gt; family crest.  My family has connection to this clan and I thought this would be a fun way to personalize the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cam2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making Progress&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cam3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Almost finished&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I finish up the board, I felt the lion and eagle needed some contrast with the background.  I was a little bit nervous about darkening the background.  When you’re this far along a project, there is always risk you can ruin it.  I suppose that risk is always there, but it’s more painful when you’re almost done!. I took the chance and started to burn the background in a swirling motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/final_cam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Final Cam&quot; /&gt;
And I’m glad I did! It’s not perfect, but I like the rustic flag and it feels good to play on. I haven’t quite settled on the playing pieces yet, so that will be another project to work on…&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Modern Abstract Spotlight: Chameleon by Logy Games</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/28/modern-abstract-spotlight-chameleon/"/>
   <updated>2019-07-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/28/modern-abstract-spotlight-chameleon</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re a fan of light chess variants and unique components, you’ll love Chameleon by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.logygames.com/english/index.html&quot;&gt;Logy Games&lt;/a&gt;.
Mitsuo Yamamoto is the designer behind the game and the company which produces these hand-made ceramic sets.  At its core, Chameleon is a small chess game reduced to the movements of kings, knights and bishops.  Every piece has a “nature” and can always move one space any direction like a king.  The “nature” is essentially the middle color of each piece (black or white).  This determines if a piece can move like a knight or bishop depending on what square it’s on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variable moves can be summed up with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the piece’s nature matches the square color, it moves like a bishop.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;If the piece’s nature doesn’t match the square, it moves like a knight.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal is to either capture all your opponents pieces or move one of your pieces to the other side of the board without being captured on the next move.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chameleon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chameleon Game Setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would highly recommend it to any fans of simple abstract strategy games.  If you want to give it a try, it’s pretty easy to make your own version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is also a print and play image that was made available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/logygames/chameleon-a-modern-version-of-chess/description&quot;&gt;Kickstarter campaign page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Chameleon_PNP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chameleon Print and Play&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of TAFL by Jesse Robinson</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/24/tafl-book.review/"/>
   <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/24/tafl-book.review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/37jCghj&quot;&gt;TAFL&lt;/a&gt; an e-book by Jesse Robinson is one of the first books about hnefatafl.  It takes a conversational approach and feels like you just had a good conversation with a random guy at the bookstore.  In just 52 pages, he shows his disdain for video games, explains how board games connect us to the past and introduces the system of tafl games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem with hnefatafl and the tafl family of games is the lack of standardized rules.  Every one seems to play them slightly differently.  I really like how Robinson introduces the tafl games by the characteristics they have in common and how they can differ into the plethora of variations that exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book lists out 9 &lt;strong&gt;common&lt;/strong&gt; characteristics as defined by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The playing board always have an odd number of squares (7x7, 9x9, 11x11, 13x13).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All pieces move orthogonally like a rook in chess.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game is asymmetric. One side (the attackers) always has more pieces than the other (the defenders).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The defender’s goal is to get their king to safety.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces are captured by being sandwiched between two of the enemy pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king can go into the center or corner squares.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The center and corner squares are “hostile squares” in capturing.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For example:&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
      If there is a piece next to one of these square, the opponent can move next
      to your piece and capture it as though one of the hostile square contained an
      enemy piece.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no suicide.  You can safely move in between two enemy pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are not allowed to jump or move through other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book also describes 8 variations that can &lt;strong&gt;differ&lt;/strong&gt; from game to game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the size of the board?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which player starts first?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can pieces can move through the center square?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the king’s escape to the corner squares or the edge?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can pieces can go back to their original starting position?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can pieces go onto opponents starting position?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the starting position for the two sides?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the king weaponless? i.e. Can the king participate in capturing other pieces?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This description of characteristics and variations is followed by some history with a notable mention
to Swedish botanist Carl Linneaus.  Who in 1732, came across the game of Tablut (a 9x9 variant) while touring &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lapland_%28Finland%29&quot;&gt;Lapland&lt;/a&gt; and recorded the rules in his diary.  These rules became the basis of the reconstruction of many tafl games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next chunk of the book is dedicated to 11 particular variations and their rules.  It’s safe to say that each set of rules presented here are not written in stone and you may find different rules elsewhere.  But they are definitely playable and represent a version of each of the following games:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ard Ri  &lt;br /&gt;
Brandubh  &lt;br /&gt;
Fitchneal  &lt;br /&gt;
Gwyddbwyll  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2ZxIA2c&quot;&gt;Tablut&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
Tawlbwrdd (2 variations)  &lt;br /&gt;
Hnefatafl (3 variations)  &lt;br /&gt;
Alea Evangelii&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/tafl_kindle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tafl Book Pic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are helpful diagrams of starting positions included with each section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The books concludes with the position that some may argue the exact rules presented in the book lacks  historic authenticity.  Robinson’s answer to that?  It doesn’t matter.  There’s no real way to prove it one way or the other and it’s more important to just get a game on the table and start playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this is a good and easy introduction to tafl games. The author’s personal commentary is interesting and is becoming more and more relevant in this digital age.  TAFL is book 1 of a series on ancient games that I hope to see continue.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Traditional Xiang Qi or Not?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/05/30/traditional-xiangqi-or-not/"/>
   <updated>2019-05-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/30/traditional-xiangqi-or-not</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I remember learning to play Xiang Qi (or Chinese Chess) as a young child.  I was 6 or 7 and my uncle spent time teaching me all the characters and the moves on a traditional set. Xiang Qi pieces, unlike Western Chess, are simple discs with Chinese characters on them.  Since I was a child, I was able to pick it up pretty quickly.  It’s a great chess variant and although tons of  people play it (because let’s face it, there are a lot of Chinese people in the world), I feel that it doesn’t get the international audience it deserves.  This is probably due to the fact that it’s intimidating to learn the characters on the pieces and to make things worse, in some cases, the characters are different depending what side you’re on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So needless to say, I was really excited to find a relatively &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2SE4yPu&quot;&gt;cheap copy on Amazon&lt;/a&gt; (I think I spent about $17 on it) with figures instead of the traditional discs.  I figured (no pun intended) this would be a great set to teach others with including my own young children.  The set is quite nice and for the price I really don’t think I could have gotten a better set. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/xiangqi-figures1.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Xiang Qi Set&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/xiangqi-figures2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Xiang Qi Set Closeup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was setting up the pieces and showing my daughter how to play, I felt strange not showing her on a traditional set.  Maybe it’s because that’s the way I learned, or maybe it felt less authentic with the figures.  Either way, it didn’t feel quite right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it’s a requirement to play or learn on a traditional set. I’ve read debates on the merits of learning the traditional way vs. using “internationalized pieces.”  I’ve heard people say that it’s better to take the time to learn the game the way it was meant to be played.  I’ve also heard arguments on the other side for lowering the barrier to entry with language agnostic pieces.  It’s likely I will end up playing with my kids on both types but it was interesting that I had an emotional response about it.  And that emotional response brought back fun child hood memories playing with my family.&lt;br /&gt;
Perhaps above all else, that is the real tradition that’s important.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Puluc Design Iteration</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/11/01/puluc-v2/"/>
   <updated>2018-11-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/01/puluc-v2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wanting to iterate over the design of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgames.xyz/2018/06/08/photoblog-puluc/&quot;&gt;Puluc board I had previously made.&lt;/a&gt;  In particular, I wanted to clean up the lines in the stairs in both of the homebase sections.
I found that the trick to burning fine lines is turning down the heat.  That gave me more control  &lt;br /&gt;
over the drawing and lead to less charred bleeding.  Adding shaded patterns also improved the overall look and feel and
made it look less like an xylophone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing I did was added a decorative pattern to the binary dice.  I was tempted to sand the corners but found the sharpness
of the cubes reinforced the decorations and added to the cut-throat nature of this running/fight game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were a few minor changes but I think they made a real difference on how the board turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Puluc Version 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Yoté Board and Elephants</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/10/18/photoblog-yote/"/>
   <updated>2018-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/18/photoblog-yote</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I used to work for a company that hosted annual employee art shows.  This was a great way to share creative passions with coworkers and I participated one year
with a wall full (10-12) of elephant paintings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been looking for a way to incorporate elephants into one of my board games and making a Yoté board was the perfect excuse (as well as it being a fun game!).
Wood burning on red oak can be a little tricky but I was pleased with the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/yote-1-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yote 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/yote-2-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yote 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/yote-3-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yote 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/yote-4-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yote 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Yoté</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/27/how-to-play-yote/"/>
   <updated>2018-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/27/how-to-play-yote</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yoté is a highly addicting strategy game from West Africa.  &lt;br /&gt;
It is played on a 5x6 board with 24 pieces and possesses an interesting capturing characteristic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/yote.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yote&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game board starts off empty with each player possessing 12 pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking turns, players may make one of these moves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place 1 piece on any empty square (only available move on first turn).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move one piece orthogonally 1 space (space must be empty).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture by jumping over an opponent’s piece othogonally. Once a piece is captured, remove from
the board.  The capturing player may now take another piece off the board of their choosing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to captured all their opponents pieces wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A World of Chess Review</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/07/27/a-world-of-chess-review/"/>
   <updated>2018-07-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/07/27/a-world-of-chess-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage on books about chess.  A quick look on the internet in your favorite search engine will produce overwhelming results.  There are books on the history of chess, the strategy of chess, chess variants, famous chess players and introductions for beginners.  So when I was looking for a book about chess, there was plenty to choose from.  I started off by picking up a copy of Murray’s History of Chess.  Written in 1913, it is a well known classic with a comprehensive look at the origins of chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t make it pass page 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I’m sure it’s worth reading (and I still hope to finish it one day), I found it to be really dense and just a beast to read.  That led me to picking up &lt;a href=&quot;http://aworldofchess.com/&quot;&gt;A World of Chess&lt;/a&gt; by Jean-Louis Cazaux &amp;amp; Rick Knowlton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, A World of Chess was just easy to read from the beginning to end.  It takes the reader on a journey around the world and into the past through the lens of chess variants and evolution.  The book is divided into sections with the focus on a certain region.  Every chapter gives a description of the variant and the history behind them.  This includes excerpts of poems, other history books and archaeological finds.  Every variant described is interesting in its own right, but a handful really stood out to me: Shatranj (an ancient version from the Persian Empire), Janggi (Korean Chess), Tori Shogi (Japanese variation based on birds). Makruk (Thai version of chess still played in Thailand today) and Gala (of Germanic origin with some interesting similarities to Hnefatafl).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last section deals with the ever burning question,”Where did chess come from?”  The origins of chess have traditionally thought to be from India.  But the authors take a thoughtful approach on presenting different compelling theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading a history book about chess may seem like a daunting task but Jean-Louis Cazaux &amp;amp; Rick Knowlton makes it a delightful experience.  The content is presented in an engaging manner that keeps the reader reading and not wanting it to end.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/aworldofchess.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A World of Chess Book&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Puluc</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/07/03/how-to-play-puluc/"/>
   <updated>2018-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/07/03/how-to-play-puluc</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Puluc finds its origins from Central America, played by the Ketchi people who are said to be descendants of the Mayans.  It is traditionally played with corn husks and is a wonderful ancient filler game.  Much of the game relies on luck, but it is a strangely satisfying game that often times can end in less than 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup-the-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup the Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc.png&quot; alt=&quot;Puluc&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each player places their pieces on their respective home bases at the end of the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-throws&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Throws&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 4 casting sticks or tokens that dictate movement of pieces.  &lt;br /&gt;
Binary dice or coins would work as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After throwing the casting sticks/tokens/dice the value of the movement is
as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 marked side up, move 1 space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 marked sides up, move 2 spaces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 marked sides up, move 3 spaces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 marked sides up, move 4 spaces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 blank sides up, move 5 spaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 3: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player that throws the highest value start first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players alternate throwing the casting tokens and moving one of their pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players may move a piece from their home base onto the track or a piece that is already on the track forward (assuming it’s not captured).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players can not land on top of their own piece.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player’s piece lands on an opponent’s, it is now captured and moves as 1 unit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a captured stack moves into the opponent’s home base.  The opponent pieces are removed from the board and the player put their piece back on their home base to start on the track again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is not allowed to capture an opponent in their home base (i.e. pieces that are not on the track yet).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Captured pieces can be “captured back” by landing on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to captured all their opponents pieces wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Photoblog: Making a Senet-Ur Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/19/photoblog-senet-ur/"/>
   <updated>2018-06-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/19/photoblog-senet-ur</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://a4games.company/senet-ur/&quot;&gt;Senet-Ur&lt;/a&gt; is a hybrid of two ancient games by &lt;a href=&quot;https://a4games.company/&quot;&gt;A4 Games&lt;/a&gt;.  As its name suggests, it combines the rules and board layout from both Senet and the Royal Game of Ur.  I actually quite like the name “Senet-Ur” because it makes me want to pronounce it like “senator.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the beginning of any game, I started with the grid layout.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/senet-ur1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Senet-Ur Board 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then continue with the square designs.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/senet-ur2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Senet-Ur Board 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/senet-ur3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Senet-Ur Board 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once done, I coated the board with 3 layers of sanding sealant and polished with beeswax.  The pieces and casting tokens are also hand rubbed with beeswax.  The brown pieces are stained with several layers of coffee.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/senet-ur4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Senet-Ur Board 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some issues with the board not quite sitting flat so I added some tripod style legs.  This ensures the board will not wobble (unless you press down hard on a corner).  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/senet-ur5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Senet-Ur Board 4&quot; /&gt;
I was quite happy with how the set turned out and even more happy to play a few rounds.  I love the creativity of combining two ancient games to produce something that is unique yet familiar.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Photoblog: Making a Puluc Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/08/photoblog-puluc/"/>
   <updated>2018-06-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/08/photoblog-puluc</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Start off by drawing out the lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc-1-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Puluc Board 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burn a pyramid in home city/base sections (the two end spaces).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc-2-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Puluc Board 2&quot; /&gt;
The end sections seem a bit plain so I shade the sky area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc-3-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Puluc Board 3&quot; /&gt;
I need to woodburn the rest of the lines and shade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc-4-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Puluc Board 4&quot; /&gt;
The playing area is done and I burn the edges to make the board look more finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc-5-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Puluc Board 5&quot; /&gt;
Now for the casting sticks and playing pieces.  I paint popsicle sticks and stain 1 set of tokens with coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/puluc-6-photoblog.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Making a Puluc Board 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still need to coat the board with sanding sealant and beeswax, but the set is functional and ready for a couple of games!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Busy Royal Game of Ur Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/23/busy-royal-game-of-ur/"/>
   <updated>2018-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/23/busy-royal-game-of-ur</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve done a lot of experimenting with making Royal Game of Ur sets.  The famous set that most people are familiar with at the British Museum is visually beautiful and busy.  &lt;br /&gt;
I’ve experimented with some more minimal designs like the one below.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/minimal_ur.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur Minimal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my latest board, I embraced the busyness.  I’ve made the board even more busy and it’s an interesting contrast to my minimalistic approach.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/busy_ur.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur Busy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This board is made with Red Oak plywood.  Red Oak is beautiful with amazing grains, but not actually the best for shading with a wood burner.  I found more success with using textures and I think it complements the board pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Pulijudam</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/01/02/how-to-play-pulijudam/"/>
   <updated>2018-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/02/how-to-play-pulijudam</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pulijudam is a game much like &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/05/17/how-to-play-fox-and-geese/&quot;&gt;Fox and Geese&lt;/a&gt; out of India.  Also known as Tigers and Lambs, it is an asymmetrical game played on the intersections of a triangular board.  There are 3 tiger pieces and 15 lamb pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1-place-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pulijudam.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pulijudam&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Tiger player places their pieces as the diagram shows.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lamb player takes the remaining 15 pieces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lamb player starts and places a piece on any empty point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lamb player can not move any pieces until all 15 pieces are placed on the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Tiger player can move one space to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the Lamb player can move a piece, it also can move to any adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Tiger player can capture a single lamb by jumping over it onto an unoccupied point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lambs can not jump over/capture tigers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Lambs win if it traps the tigers so they can no longer move.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Tigers win if they capture all the lambs.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Making of a Go Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/12/making-a-go-board/"/>
   <updated>2017-12-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/12/12/making-a-go-board</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently made a Go board for a friend’s kid.  It’s the second one I’ve done and I really enjoyed the process.  Initially, I felt a bit intimidated about making one in the first place.  Why?  Go boards have a long history of precision and meticulous 
craftmanship which is really different from the rustic style of my game boards.  At the end of the day, it’s all really about 
fun and friendship so I was happy to present what I had.  The board is a 9x9 grid, decorated with bamboo and panda illustrations.
The lighter pieces are natural colored, finished with beeswax.  The darker pieces were stained with 10-12 coats of coffee.
Overall, I was happy with what I ended up with and hope my friend’s son have many years of enjoyment from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/go1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Go Board 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/go2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Go Board 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/go_board_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Go Board 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Egg Carton Mancala</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/02/egg-carton-mancala/"/>
   <updated>2017-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/10/02/egg-carton-mancala</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was recently interested in learning how to play Wari which is a West African game from the Mancala family.  There are a ton of buying options out there, but I wanted to play a few games before purchasing a set.
I came across a mention of using an empty egg carton and 48 pieces of whatever you can find.&lt;br /&gt;
You would need to fit at least 4 pieces in each cup for the initial setup.  Coins, coffee beans, rocks or buttons would work.
I happened to have a bunch of wooden tokens that fit perfectly.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/egg-carton-mancala.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Egg Carton Mancala&quot; /&gt;
Although it wouldn’t replace getting a nice set, it worked out pretty well for trial purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Painting Resin</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/30/diy-painting-resin/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/30/diy-painting-resin</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Casting resin pieces is a great way to make game pieces.  Depending on the resin color, you may want to further enhance your pieces with some custom painting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgames.xyz/2016/10/27/diy-resin-king/&quot;&gt;previous blog&lt;/a&gt;, the white resin was great for a casting the chess pawn because it matched the stone-like quality of the piece.
With other shapes, a little paint can go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the case of casting &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgames.xyz/2016/10/07/lewis-chessmen-unmasked-review/&quot;&gt;Lewis Chessmen&lt;/a&gt; pieces for various Hnefatafl sets.  The white resin made them look like cheap plastic pieces.  In order to solve this problem and make the pieces look more pleasing, I dug back into my art major college days. 
There is a painting technique called scumbling which modifies a base paint color by applying a very thin coat of paint (of a different color) on top.  The bottom layer still shows through and the result is a canvas color that is richer.
This technique can be applied to resin pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with a dark base color, paint the piece until the white resin is completely covered.  I found something like a raw umber is perfect in that it is dark but not as hard as a straight black.  Once the piece is dry, take a little bit of an accent color and lightly brush it over the piece.  An iron oxide over a raw umber looks pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the piece dry and spray some protective acrylic coating and you end up with a pretty nice piece to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/painting-resin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Resin Painting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Print and Play the Royal Game of Ur</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/13/royal-game-or-ur-pnp/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/13/royal-game-or-ur-pnp</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Print and plays are a great way to try out games before investing money on a nice set.  In some cases, especially
with independent game designers, it’s the only way to play their games.  They are also great for classroom use or
group use.  If anything, it’s fun and cheap entertainment.  I recently explored creating one for the Royal Game of Ur
using pocket change for pieces and casting tokens. It was a fun experiment and for those interested, I was able to create the entire PDF (diagrams
and all) using Google Docs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur-pnp-preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur Print and Play&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur-pnp.pdf&quot;&gt;download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;, grab a pocket full of change and some friends to
re-live those college budget nights. :) Happy Gaming!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Senet</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/12/how-to-play-senet/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/12/how-to-play-senet</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Senet is an ancient Egyptian board game played on a 3x10 grid board.  It was being played before 3000 B.C. and have been
found in burial tombs.  One of the most eleaborate boards belonged to King Tutankhamun.  No rules have survived and many
game historians have sought to reconstruct the game.  These rules are by British Museum curator, Irving Finkel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/senet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Senet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 7 pieces and they are placed on the top half of the board alternating colors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After the board is setup, the first player takes 4 casting tokens and throws them to determine the value how much to
move their piece.  The value is determined by how many marked sides are up.  If no marked sides are showing the value is 5.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can only move forwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can land on a vacant spot or swap places with an opponent’s piece if it’s &lt;em&gt;undefended&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have two pieces right next to each other on adjacent squares, they defend each other and therefore cannot be swapped.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you throw a 1, 4 or 5.  You get to throw again. 
 (All throws must be complete before moving pieces)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sum of multiple throws can be divided among several of your pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You cannot swap pieces that are on safe squares.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last 5 squares are special:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Square 26&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square, must throw 5 to leave this space.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 27&lt;/strong&gt;: Water square, go back to the beginning of the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 28&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 29&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square, must throw 2 to leave this space.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 30&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square, must throw 1 to leave this space.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player able to get all 7 of their pieces off the board wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Five Lines</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/31/how-to-play-five-lines/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/31/how-to-play-five-lines</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Five Lines was a game originating from Ancient Greece where it was known as Penta Grammai.  The earliest reference to it is in 600 B.C. in a verse by Greek poet, Alkaios.  It became popular among the Romans and boards have been found etched into
pavements of old Roman towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/five_lines.png&quot; alt=&quot;Five Liness&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 5 pieces and places them on their side of the board (one per line/rectangle).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player take turns rolling a single die and moves one of their pieces counterclockwise according to the die value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only 1 piece is allowed per line, so pieces are only allowed to move to a vacant spot.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The exception is the middle line (called the sacred line) is where more than 1 piece can land.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player must move a piece even if it means moving a piece off the sacred line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player is unable to move into a vacant spot or the sacred line, they pass.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player able to get all 5 of their pieces onto the sacred line of the opposing side wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Five Men's Morris</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/25/how-to-play-five-mens-morris/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/25/how-to-play-five-mens-morris</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Five Men’s Morris is a merels game from Europe.  It also almost identical to Six Men’s Morris which only differs
by the fact that each player gets an extra piece.  Diagrams of the board have been found in 16th century manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1-place-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/five.png&quot; alt=&quot;Five Men's Morris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 5 pieces and take turns placing them on the board with the intention of trying to make 3 in a row.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces should be placed on any place where there is an intersection of lines (corners included).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once all the pieces are placed, the first player moves one of its pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can move along a line to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a player forms a row of 3, they are to remove an opponent’s piece off the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capturing/Removing a piece that is part of a row of 3 is not allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A player loses when they are down to 2 pieces.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Three Men's Morris</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/20/how-to-play-three-mens-morris/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/20/how-to-play-three-mens-morris</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Three Men’s Morris is a simple strategy game played by the ancient Romans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1-place-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/three.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three Men's Morris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 3 pieces and take turns placing them on the board with the intention of trying to make 3 in a row.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces should be placed on any place where there is an intersection of lines (corners included).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once all the pieces are placed, the first player moves one of its pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can move along a line to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players take turns moving their pieces until someone gets three in a row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to make three in a row wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Roman Cats - A Retheming of Shut the Box</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/03/retheming-shut-the-box/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/03/retheming-shut-the-box</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Retheming is a fun way to breathe new life into old abstract games.  I recently experimented with making wooden Roman numeral dice and that is where the idea began.  Shut the Box is an old English pub game that is still fairly popular today.  There are many variations and sets available online.&lt;br /&gt;
I was thinking about how to make a set without having to construct the actual box.  It’s a super simple game that could be potentially played using just a deck of card and set of dice.  With this in mind, I made 9 cat tokens, each with a Roman numeral across the top.  My 11 year old nephew and his friend assisted me with the cat drawings.
 &lt;strong&gt;Roman Cats&lt;/strong&gt;, a kitty themed version of Shut the Box was born!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/roman-cats-finished.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roman Cats&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-play&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Play&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the 9 cat tokens in a row with the Roman numerals facing up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine the first player&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 1st player starts by rolling the set of dice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The player takes any combination of available numbered tokens that add up to the
sum of the rolled dice.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For example, a player rolls a 4 and 5 (total 9). They may take any available tokens that add up to 9:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
 9  &lt;br /&gt;
 4, 5   &lt;br /&gt;
 1, 3, 5  &lt;br /&gt;
 1, 8&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After the first player takes the appropriate tokens, the 2nd player rolls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players alternate until no more tokens are left to take&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player rolls and is unable to take tokens, their turn is over (no rerolls)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the token with the number 1 is the only one remaining, players may use 1 die to roll&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game ends with there are no more cat tokens, each player then adds up there score.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The player with the highest score wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Optional End Rules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The player who takes the last token receives an extra 6 points&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the player who took the last token is winning by less than 6 points, the losing player has a chance to roll both dice again.  If they roll exactly a 6, they also receive 6 bonus points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Roman numerals added an additional learning element since you have to know your Roman numerals to play!  It might also be interesting to make a Chinese version with Kanji characters. In any event, retheming games is a great way to include family and friends in interacting via board games.  My nephew and his friend (who both happen to love cats) approved and enjoyed a game that they may have not otherwise played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know not everyone has the equipment to make custom wooden pieces.  The wood burning kit itself can be a sizable investment.  If you want to try the game out, feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/roman-cats-pnp.pdf&quot;&gt;download the print and play&lt;/a&gt; version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/roman-cats-pnp-preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Roman Cats Print and Play&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either cut out the cards or place coins to designate which cat number is taken.  With this print out and a set of dice, you’ll be ready to play.  Happy Gaming!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Games - Discover and Play 5 Famous Ancient Games</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/06/03/discover-and-play-review/"/>
   <updated>2017-06-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/06/03/discover-and-play-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the individual discovering the beauty of ancient games, &lt;strong&gt;Games - Discover and Play 5 Famous Ancient Games&lt;/strong&gt; by Irving Finkel 
is a great gentle introduction into that world.  It is originally a children’s activity book published by the British Museum.
It takes a child (and the child at heart) through 5 different ancient race games: Duodecim Scripta, Royal Game of Ur, Ancient Egyptian Senet, Pachisi,
&amp;amp; Snakes and Ladders.  At just 36 pages, it is filled with interesting history and great pictures of ancient gaming artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes this book unique is the inclusion of colorful fold-out boards, punch-out pieces and rules for each game.  So not only do you get a great historical introduction, but the opportunity to &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; play the games!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-pachisi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pachisi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is definitely a nice aspect since most of these games are a bit hard to come by and it is a great way to
try out each game before investing in nicer sets.  The boards and the rules are really the gems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-senet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Senet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The punch-out pieces are not as compelling (Though to be fair, this is true for  almost any print and play game).  It would probably be better to use tokens or coins instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-punchout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punch out&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it’s still a book worth picking up.  At the time of this writing, I picked up the book on Amazon for $1.99 plus shipping.  The last time I looked, there were quite a few still available.  For a few dollars, it’s a steal for an evening of history and fun wrapped up in a compact book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Fox and Geese</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/17/how-to-play-fox-and-geese/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/17/how-to-play-fox-and-geese</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fox and Geese is a northern European hunt game played with 13 geese and 1 fox.  Its asymmetrical nature is similar to that of hnefatafl.  Some theorize there is a relationship between two.  Queen Victoria is said to also be a fan on this medieval game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup-the-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup the Board&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arrange the 13 geese  pieces on the board according to the following layout:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fox-geese.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fox and Geese&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fox player may place their piece on any empty point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The geese starts the game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geese may move along any line going from point to point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fox also moves along lines like the geese.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fox capures a goose by jumping over it into a vacant spot (like checkers), as long as the jump is along a line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If possible, the fox is allowed to capture another goose if in a position to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geese can not capture the fox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The geese wins if the trap the fox so that it may no longer move.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The fox wins if it captures enough (10) geese so that it can’t be trapped.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a slight advantage to the geese so switching sides will balance out the game.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Nine Men's Morris</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/07/how-to-to-play-nine-mens-morris/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/07/how-to-to-play-nine-mens-morris</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nine Men’s Morris is an ancient game with an unknown origin.  Historic boards
have been found in Troy, Ireland, and Egypt.  The Romans took it across its empire and it has even found it’s way on the back of Viking Hnefatafl boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup-the-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup the Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/nine.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nine Men's Morris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black starts the placement phase of the game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 9 pieces and take turns placing them on the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces should be placed on any place where there is an intersection of lines (corners included).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black starts the movement phase of the game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can move along a line to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a player has 3 of its own pieces in a row (called a mill), the player can then remove one of the opponent’s pieces from the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can not remove an opponent’s piece if it is part of a mill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player is down to 3 pieces, they can move a piece to any vacant spot on the board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to capture all but 2 of the opponent pieces wins .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a slight advantage to the first player so switching who starts
first will balance out the game.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Seega</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/03/how-to-play-seega/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/03/how-to-play-seega</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Seega is a small abstract game from 19th century Egypt.  It has some similarities with the tafl family of games with its sandwiching capture method.  It is
played on a 5x5 grid with 24 pieces (12 per player).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup-the-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup the Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/seega.png&quot; alt=&quot;Seega&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each player gets 12 pieces and take turns placing 2 pieces on the board, leaving the middle square empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The last player to place a piece starts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can  move horizontally or vertically to an adjacent square (like a rook that can only move 1 space at a time).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces are allowed on the center square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player is unable to move, the other player takes an extra turn to create an opening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece is captured when a player is able to sandwich an opponent’s piece horizontally or vertically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capturing more than one piece with 1 move is possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving in between two enemy pieces is permitted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The center square is a safe place and a piece on it can’t be captured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to capture all the opponent pieces wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play the Royal Game of Ur</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/25/how-to-play-the-royal-game-of-ur/"/>
   <updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/25/how-to-play-the-royal-game-of-ur</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Royal Game of Ur dates back to 2600 B.C.  It is the most complete ancient board game known to date. In 1926, Sir Leonard Woolley discovered the board and pieces while excavating the royal tombs in Ur.  This ancient Mesopotamian city is located in now modern day Iraq and is said to be the birthplace of Abraham (Genesis 11:31).  British Museum’s curator Irving Finkel &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wHjznvH54Cw&quot;&gt;discovered the rules&lt;/a&gt; on a cuneiform tablet where both the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=8817&amp;amp;partId=1&quot;&gt;board and tablet are on display&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-start-with-a-blank-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Start with a Blank Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur.png&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player receives 7 pieces and 3 casting tokens (can be sticks, coins, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The starting player casts their 3 tokens, count the value, and move a piece that many spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player 1 starts by entering a piece through the square marked with the letter ‘A’ and follow the path off the board to letter ‘B’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur-path.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Path&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Player 2 follows a similar path but on their side.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you land a square occupied by the other player’s piece &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; it’s not on a marked square, the opponent’s piece is knocked off the board and must start over.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a piece is on a marked square, it is safe from being knocked off.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you land a marked square, you can cast/roll again.  You don’t necessarily have to move that piece.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you made your way around the path, you must roll/cast the exact value to leave the board.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to move all 7 of their pieces off the board wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play French Military Game</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/02/20/how-to-play-french-military-game/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/20/how-to-play-french-military-game</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The French Military Game is a 19th century game played with just 4 pieces: 3 hunters and 1 prey.
It was popular among French officers during the Franco-Prussian War of 1870-71.
Also known as Hare &amp;amp; Hounds, it is one of the smallest hunt games.  Mathematician Martin
Gardner, writer of monthly column “Mathematical Games” in Scientific American stated that
the game “combines extreme simplicity with extraordinary strategic subtley.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/french-military-game-layout1.png&quot; alt=&quot;French Military Game Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The hunter starts first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The hunter may move a piece one spot along a line to the right horizontally, diagonally or vertically.
(i.e. Hunters can’t move backwards).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The prey may move one step in any direction along a line (backwards or forwards).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hunters wins by trapping the prey so that it can no longer move.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Prey wins by passing all the hunters and reaching the other end of the board.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the hunter doesn’t advance to the right in 10 moves, the prey wins.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Fanorona</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/31/how-to-play-fanorona/"/>
   <updated>2016-12-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/31/how-to-play-fanorona</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fanorona is a game from Madagascar that dates back to 1680.  It is a beautiful game
played with 44 pieces (22 per player) and has a unique method of capturing.
The game has experienced a bit of a revival in modern times due to its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vn5WIwlYY6Y&quot;&gt;inclusion
in the Assassin’s Creed&lt;/a&gt; video game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/640px-Fanorona.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fanorona Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;White starts first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move from one point to another along a line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture by moving a piece directly towards a line of enemies (approach).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture by moving a piece away from a line of enemies (withdrawal).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove captured pieces immediately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player may continue to capture pieces via approach or withdrawal as long as
the enemies are on separate lines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player must capture pieces if possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only one capture is allowed on a player’s first move.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Player wins by capturing all the opponents pieces.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fanorona is a really interesting game with a rich history.  Although a derivative of the Moorish
game alquerque, the unique capturing methods makes it stand solidly on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Sea Battle Tafl</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/11/06/how-to-play-sea-battle-tafl/"/>
   <updated>2016-11-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/06/how-to-play-sea-battle-tafl</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sea Battle Tafl is a modern variation of hnefatafl.  It is played on a 9x9 board with a total 25 of pieces much like &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgames.xyz/2016/09/25/how-to-play-tablut/&quot;&gt;Tablut&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/354px-Tablut_board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tablut Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cargo ship piece goes on the central square surrounded by defenders.  &lt;br /&gt;
The attacker/pirate ship pieces surround the defenders making a cross symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defenders start first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are no special squares.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the cargo ship leaves the central square anyone can occupy it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on 2 sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pirates capture the cargo ship by surrounding it on 4 sides.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cargo ship is without weapons and can’t aid in capturing pirates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can voluntarily enter a space between two enemies and not be captured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the cargo ship to an edge.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacking pirates wins by capturing the cargo ship.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Casting a Resin King</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/27/diy-resin-king/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/27/diy-resin-king</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the many enduring qualities of tafl games is the simplicity of the pieces.   No matter what size board or what rule variation (with perhaps the exception of &lt;a href=&quot;http://aagenielsen.dk/berserk_rules.php&quot;&gt;Berserk Hnefatafl&lt;/a&gt;), a set only need pieces of 3 distinctions: attackers, defenders and a king.  This makes it easier to create your own set.  It is common to see decorative glass gems as hnefatafl pieces.  In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.richgames.xyz/2016/10/24/diy-brandub/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, we started to make a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.richgames.xyz/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/&quot;&gt;Basic Brandub&lt;/a&gt; game with these.  Let’s upgrade the set a bit with a hand-casted resin king piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tucked away in a drawer, I had an old chess pawn given to me by my best friend in grade school.  I’ve had this pawn since I was 7 or 8 years old.  It reminds me of my first friendship and being that tafl games are great to play with friends, it was a fitting piece to cast.  Obviously, pick an item that works for you and give your set a personal touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chess-pawn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chess Pawn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smooth-on.com/products/oomoo-30/&quot;&gt;silicone mold making kit&lt;/a&gt;, I carefully follow the instructions and made a mold of the chess pawn.  This stuff is messy and gooey, so be sure to wear gloves and cover the work area with newspapers.  The mold takes about 6 hours to cure, so be patient.  It took a few tries to get it right, but the result was a durable mold I can use over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many types of resin to choose from.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alumilite.com/store/p/934-Alumilite-White-Amazing-Casting-Resin.aspx&quot;&gt;Alumilite makes a fast curing, beginner friendly resin&lt;/a&gt; that works great for small pieces.  Like the mold making kit, it’s important to follow the instructions carefully and use gloves while casting the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 20 minutes, I had a perfect copy of my original chess pawn that makes a great king piece in the &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/&quot;&gt;Basic Brandub&lt;/a&gt; set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chess-pawn-cast.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chess Pawn Cast&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One game’s pawn is another game’s king. Such is life.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Make a Brandub Set</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/24/diy-brandub/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/24/diy-brandub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Making board games can be a fun, creative and sometimes frustrating adventure. There is something wonderful about playing a game with family and friends on something created by your own hands.  This is the first in a series of Do-It-Yourself blog articles on how to do just that and some of the lessons learned in the process. In this first article, we will describe the beginnings steps in making a &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/&quot;&gt;Basic Brandub&lt;/a&gt; set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-board&quot;&gt;The Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foundation of every board game is…well…the board.  Our Basic Brandub set uses an 8 inch square board.  Your best bet is to go to a local lumber supplier to purchase some plywood and get it cut down to that size.  There are also some online options.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.craftparts.com/&quot;&gt;Woodworks Ltd.&lt;/a&gt; sells individual &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.craftparts.com/plywood-square-cutouts-p-5093.html&quot;&gt;8x8 squares that are 1/8 inch&lt;/a&gt; thick for relatively cheap.  If you don’t mind spending a bit more, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kencraftcompany.com/&quot;&gt;KenCraft Company&lt;/a&gt; has a great selection of plywood and if you email them they will cut it down to the size you want for a fee.  Be warned you will be spending more on cutting fees and shipping than on the plywood itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the piece of plywood, sand it down to the desired smoothness.  Don’t skimp too much on this step.  The more time put into the sanding, the better the board will be.  Mark out the grid using 1 inch squares and a 1/2 inch border.  This will produce a 7x7 Brandub board where the gameplay happens on the squares (in oppose to the intersections).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a woodburning pen and a metal ruler, burn the lines in.  Unfortunately, the metal will draw heat from the woodburning pen and cause the lines to be a bit inconsistent in darkness.   Don’t dismay and just keep going.  When all the lines are done, carefully go over the lines again without the ruler to fill in any gaps.  Burn an ‘x’ into the corner and center squares.  Coat the board with a layer of sanding sealant, let it dry (about 1/2 hour) and smooth with #0000 steel wool (super fine grade).  Finally, finish with beeswax.  It is also possible to skip the sanding sealant and just use beeswax.  The surface won’t be as hard or smooth but the beeswax will produce a lovely finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pieces&quot;&gt;The Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brandub requires 13 pieces: 8 attackers, 4 defenders and 1 king.  This can
be easily accomplished with different colored glass gems. These are commonly
found in hobby stores for decorative purposes.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hobbylobby.com/&quot;&gt;Hobby Lobby&lt;/a&gt; is a great resource with a variety of colors and sizes.  The standard size (around 18mm) will fit the 1 inch squares pretty nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You now have a complete and playable Brandub set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-brandub-gems.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brandub&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for the next article and upgrade your set by casting a king piece in resin.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Fetlar Hnefatafl</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/12/how-to-play-fetlar-hnefatafl/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/12/how-to-play-fetlar-hnefatafl</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Fetlar rule variant is a common and popular way to play hnefatafl on a 11x11 board. There are 37 total pieces,
24 attackers, 12 defenders and 1 king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Hnefatafl_11x11_board.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Fetlar  Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The king piece goes on the central square surrounded by his defenders forming a diamond shape.
The attacker pieces surround the defenders along the perimeter of the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers start first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king piece can go to the corner squares or central square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other pieces can pass through the central square after the king leaves but can’t stop there (think freeway with no exit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on two sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture 3 pieces at most with 1 move.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture pieces against the central square and corner squares as though your piece is on it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The king is special, attackers needs to surround him on 4 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is next to the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 3 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the king to the corner square.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacker wins by capturing the king.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.  This is not really a step in the Fetlar rules as much as it’s a good chance to play both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of The Lewis Chessmen Unmasked</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/07/lewis-chessmen-unmasked-review/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/07/lewis-chessmen-unmasked-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Any fascination with the ancient game of hnefatafl will eventually lead to the Lewis Chessmen.  The most commercially available set, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2X1KfPw&quot;&gt;The Viking Game&lt;/a&gt; uses pieces inspired by them. The more motivated enthusiast have used them in DIY sets and their Norse origin is undeniable.  There are a ton of books out there about the Lewis Chessmen. The British Museum and the National Museum of Scotland put on a joint exhibition (not all the pieces belong to one museum) in 2010. &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/2YhtUmw&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lewis Chessmen: Unmasked&lt;/em&gt; by David Caldwell&lt;/a&gt; is the companion book to that exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/about_us/news_and_press/statements/the_lewis_chessmen.aspx&quot;&gt;The Lewis Chessmen&lt;/a&gt; is a collection of chess pieces dating back to the 12th century.  They were found accidentally in the
Isle of Lewis.  The book does a wonderful job of describing its mysterious discovery, its Scandanavian roots and theories about who they may have belonged to.  It’s a short (80 pages) companion book and catalogs each piece 
with beautiful photographs. Two of the pages are dedicated to connecting the chessmen to hnefatafl, suggesting that the kings doubled as pieces in both games.  There is evidence to support this notion as double-sided boards have been found at archaelogical sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is a great read and introduces these little figures in a compelling way.
Though it is a pale substitute for viewing the chessmen in real life, it does a pretty good job of fueling the intrigue. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lewis-chessmen-unmasked.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lewis Chessmen Unmasked&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Tablut</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/25/how-to-play-tablut/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/25/how-to-play-tablut</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tablut is played on a 9x9 board with a total 25 of pieces.  This includes 16 attackers, 8 defenders and 1 king.
It was played in Lapland as late as the 18th century and is the most documented hnefatafl game thanks to Swedish botanist Carl Linneaus.  In 1732, while touring the area he came across the game played by the locals and &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/stream/ungdomsskrifter02linne#page/n155/mode/2up&quot;&gt;described it in his diary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/354px-Tablut_board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tablut Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The king piece goes on the central square surrounded by his defenders.
The attacker pieces surround the defenders making a cross symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers start first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king piece can go to the central square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the king leaves the central square, he can’t go back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other pieces can pass through the central square after the king leaves but can’t stop there (think freeway with no exit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on two sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can voluntarily enter a space between two enemies and not be captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture pieces against the central square as though your piece is on it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is in the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 4 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is next to the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 3 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is anywhere else on the board he is captured like any other piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the king to an edge.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacker wins by capturing the king.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Brandub</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/how-to-play-brandub/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/how-to-play-brandub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Brandub is an Irish variant of hnefatafl.  It is played on a 7x7 board with 13 pieces.
Although it is the tiny sibling of all the hnefatafl games, it is just as fun and strategic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/283px-Brandub_board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Brandub Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The king piece goes on the central square surrounded by his defenders.
The attacker pieces surround the defenders making a cross symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers move first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king piece can go to the corner squares or central square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the king leaves the central square, he can’t go back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other pieces can pass through the central square after the king leaves but can’t stop there (think freeway with no exit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on two sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_normal_capture.png&quot; alt=&quot;Normal Capture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can voluntarily enter a space between two enemies and not be captured.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_volunteer.png&quot; alt=&quot;Voluntarily enter between two enemies&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture pieces against the central square and corner squares as though your piece is on it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is in the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 4 sides to capture.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_king_capture_4_sides.png&quot; alt=&quot;Capture on 4 sides&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is next to the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 3 sides to capture.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_king_capture_3_sides.png&quot; alt=&quot;Capture on 3 sides&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is anywhere else on the board he is captured like any other piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the king to the corner square.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacker wins by capturing the king.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is Hnefatafl?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/19/what-is-hnefatafl/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/19/what-is-hnefatafl</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Besides it’s somewhat unfortunate name, hnefatafl (pronounced “neffa-taffle”) is a wonderful ancient game the Vikings played.  Commonly thought
to be a predecessor of chess, it is much simpler but just as addicting.  Originally from
Scandanavia, as the Vikings migrated (a.k.a. raided other regions) they brought hnefatafl with
them, introducing it to the local people.
Different regions played slightly different variations of the game but the core fundamental strategy stayed the same.
The size of the board also varied depending on the local taste.  It’s kind of like how Chinese food is different but familiar no matter what country you’re in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defenders and their king always sit in the middle of the board, outnumbered by twice as many
attackers.  The board is always an odd number of squares (i.e. 7x7, 9x9, 11x11, etc.).  The defender’s 
objective is to get the king to the safety of a corner square (or edge depending on the hnefatafl version).
The attacker’s objective is to capture the king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the board and the name of the game also varied depending on the region.  The Irish variant is called
“brandub” and is played on a 7x7 board.  The Norse version seemed to be commonly played on 11x11 or 13x13 board.  &lt;br /&gt;
Tablut from Lapland is played on 9x9 board.  Today, most commercially available hnefatafl sets are on a 11x11 board.
Each version contain it’s own characteristics but all belong to the tafl family of games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most obvious attributes of hnefatafl is it’s asymmetrical nature.  The fact that one player
gets just about twice as many pieces as the other &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; very strange and unfair.  But that is one 
the many enduring qualities of this game.  Playing different sides requires different ways of thinking.
The rules are simple and easy to learn, but the gameplay is complex and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hnefatafl, like other ancient games isn’t owned by any one person or company.  It’s the open source of the physical
gaming world.  This gives people the freedom to explore without the legal issues of proprietary games.  Take a look online and you’ll find a plethora of hand-made do-it-yourself as well as mobile and online versions.
Hnefatafl is not a game most people know about.  But it’s certainly a game that is experiencing a bit of revival.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Basic Brandub</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/18/basic-brandub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/brandub-product.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brandub&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brandub is the Irish variant of the ancient Viking game of hnefatafl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This board is hand-made using 8 inch square plywood that is 3/8 inch thick.  The pattern is
burned into the wood using the pyrography technique. 
Included is a set of glass gems, 8 black attackers, 4 red defenders and
a hand-casted resin king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with many hand-made products, no two boards are alike.  There may be minor irregularities that gives
each set a unique rustic character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;WARNING: CHOKING HAZARD - This product contains small parts and is not suitable for children.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Available for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/listing/485250523/hnefatafl-brandub&quot;&gt;purchase&lt;/a&gt; on Etsy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of The Leprechaun Companion</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/06/leprechaun-companion/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/06/leprechaun-companion</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Leprechaun Companion is a wonderfully illustrated and imaginative book. It was written by Nigel Suckling, though you would be hard-pressed to actually find a copy with that name on it. He wrote this particular book under the pen name, Niall Macnamara, the name given to him by the leprechauns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally purchased this book in order to read a bit more about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unicorngarden.com/magpie.htm&quot;&gt;Magpie&lt;/a&gt;, a modern variation of brandub. Brandub is an Irish variant of hneftafl played on a 7x7 board. The author takes brandub and reimagines it with a leprechaun theme. The king is replaced with a leprechaun who is only allowed to move one space at a time due to the weight of his pot of gold. The defenders are the leprechaun’s friends assisting him to escape to a corner and the attackers are thieves trying to steal the gold. Gameplay is essentially the same as brandub with this exception (one space moves for the king piece) and the leprechaun needs to be surrounded on 4 sides in order to be captured (or 3 sides if standing next to the central square, corner squares or edge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book turned out to be a pleasant surprise. Not only did it contain this cute backstory about Magpie (the leprechaun’s favorite game), it also included a comprehensive set of rules with diagrams and two beautiful usable boards in the inside covers (you will need to provide your own pieces).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lp-magpie.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Magpie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapters are filled with delightful illustrations and stories about these magical little creatures. The author brings you into a world where fairies are real and you better pay attention to the leprechaun living in your house. Though not exactly a children’s book, the mix of fantasy, history and Irish folklore will certainly entertain the child in you.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lp-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review On The Hnefatafl Books by Damian Walker</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/07/27/hnefatafl-book-reviews/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/07/27/hnefatafl-book-reviews</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I grew up playing board games.  My uncle taught me at a very early age how to play classic
Western games such as chess and checkers.  He also taught me how to play games relating to our Chinese
culture and heritage such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jungle_(board_game)&quot;&gt;dou shou qui&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xiangqi&quot;&gt;xiang qi&lt;/a&gt;.  So it was only natural when I stumbled upon
the ancient Viking game of hfneftafl that I would instantly be fascinated by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hnefatafl is a predecessor of chess.  It is simpler to play and is sometimes called ‘Viking Chess’.  The first thing that is very apparent is that there are not a lot of sources about the history and roots of hnefatafl
in general.  Where there are tons of books about games such as chess and backgammon, book resources
on this Viking game is almost &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NaN&quot;&gt;NaN&lt;/a&gt;.  Which is why I was pleased to discover these two books
by Damian Walker, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tafl.cyningstan.com/weblinks/1346/an-introduction-to-hnefatafl&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Hnefatafl&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tafl.cyningstan.com/weblinks/1068/reconstructing-hnefatafl&quot;&gt;Reconstructing Hnefatafl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Introduction to Hnefatafl&lt;/em&gt; is exactly what it sounds like.  This little book is a great introduction
to the history of the ancient board game.  It also describes the rules of play.  It’s a quick read packed with a lot of interesting facts. 
It surveys quite a bit, covering topics from its mysterious origins to its modern revival.  In some ways, the book really paints a broad picture about the migration of
the Vikings and the game they left behind.  In just 43 pages, the book fueled my interest and made me want
to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reconstructing Hnefatafl&lt;/em&gt; takes on a more academic approach (though just as readable).  It goes through different
historical texts and reconstructs the rules of different variations of the game.  For example, the author takes a
diary written in 1732 with a fairly complete description of the game of tablut (a variation of hnefatafl) and reconstructs the rules accordingly.  Some historical texts are less comprehensive, in which Walker walks (no pun intended) us through the steps of how he fills in the gaps.  He also takes archaelogical
evidence, such as excavated game boards and meticulously deduces game play from them.  This is another short read and in 64 pages I was able to learn more about this fascinating game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, both these books are a great way to learn about hnefatafl.  The game itself is pretty fun
and these books will definitely enhance your appreciation (and your geek factor) for this little known gem.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
