<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Rich Games</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2018-05-23T23:43:17-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Liz Lam</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>A Busy Royal Game of Ur Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/23/busy-royal-game-of-ur/"/>
   <updated>2018-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/23/busy-royal-game-of-ur</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve done a lot of experimenting with making Royal Game of Ur sets.  The famous set that most people are familiar with at the British Museum is visually beautiful and busy.  &lt;br /&gt;
I’ve experimented with some more minimal designs like the one below.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/minimal_ur.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur Minimal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my latest board, I embraced the busyness.  I’ve made the board even more busy and it’s an interesting contrast to my minimalistic approach.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/busy_ur.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur Busy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This board is made with Red Oak plywood.  Red Oak is beautiful with amazing grains, but not actually the best for shading with a wood burner.  I found more success with using textures and this is what I ended up with.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Pulijudam</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/01/02/how-to-play-pulijudam/"/>
   <updated>2018-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/02/how-to-play-pulijudam</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pulijudam is a game much like &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/05/17/how-to-play-fox-and-geese/&quot;&gt;Fox and Geese&lt;/a&gt; out of India.  Also known as Tigers and Lambs, it is an asymmetrical game played on the intersections of a triangular board.  There are 3 tiger pieces and 15 lamb pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1-place-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pulijudam.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pulijudam&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Tiger player places their pieces as the diagram shows.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lamb player takes the remaining 15 pieces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lamb player starts and places a piece on any empty point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Lamb player can not move any pieces until all 15 pieces are placed on the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Tiger player can move one space to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the Lamb player can move a piece, it also can move to any adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Tiger player can capture a single lamb by jumping over it onto an unoccupied point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lambs can not jump over/capture tigers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Lambs win if it traps the tigers so they can no longer move.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Tigers win if they capture all the lambs.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Making of a Go Board</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/12/making-a-go-board/"/>
   <updated>2017-12-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/12/12/making-a-go-board</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently made a Go board for a friend’s kid.  It’s the second one I’ve done and I really enjoyed the process.  Initially, I felt a bit intimidated about making one in the first place.  Why?  Go boards have a long history of precision and meticulous 
craftmanship which is really different from the rustic style of my game boards.  At the end of the day, it’s all really about 
fun and friendship so I was happy to present what I had.  The board is a 9x9 grid, decorated with bamboo and panda illustrations.
The lighter pieces are natural colored, finished with beeswax.  The darker pieces were stained with 10-12 coats of coffee.
Overall, I was happy with what I ended up with and hope my friend’s son have many years of enjoyment from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/go1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Go Board 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/go2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Go Board 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/go_board_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Go Board 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Egg Carton Mancala</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/02/egg-carton-mancala/"/>
   <updated>2017-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/10/02/egg-carton-mancala</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was recently interested in learning how to play Wari which is a West African game from the Mancala family.  There are a ton of buying options out there, but I wanted to play a few games before purchasing a set.
I came across a mention of using an empty egg carton and 48 pieces of whatever you can find.&lt;br /&gt;
You would need to fit at least 4 pieces in each cup for the initial setup.  Coins, coffee beans, rocks or buttons would work.
I happened to have a bunch of wooden tokens that fit perfectly.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/egg-carton-mancala.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Egg Carton Mancala&quot; /&gt;
Although it wouldn’t replace getting a nice set, it worked out pretty well for trial purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Painting Resin</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/30/diy-painting-resin/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/30/diy-painting-resin</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Casting resin pieces is a great way to make game pieces.  Depending on the resin color, you may want to further enhance your pieces with some custom painting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgames.xyz/2016/10/27/diy-resin-king/&quot;&gt;previous blog&lt;/a&gt;, the white resin was great for a casting the chess pawn because it matched the stone-like quality of the piece.
With other shapes, a little paint can go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the case of casting &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgames.xyz/2016/10/07/lewis-chessmen-unmasked-review/&quot;&gt;Lewis Chessmen&lt;/a&gt; pieces for various Hnefatafl sets.  The white resin made them look like cheap plastic pieces.  In order to solve this problem and make the pieces look more pleasing, I dug back into my art major college days. 
There is a painting technique called scumbling which modifies a base paint color by applying a very thin coat of paint (of a different color) on top.  The bottom layer still shows through and the result is a canvas color that is richer.
This technique can be applied to resin pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with a dark base color, paint the piece until the white resin is completely covered.  I found something like a raw umber is perfect in that it is dark but not as hard as a straight black.  Once the piece is dry, take a little bit of an accent color and lightly brush it over the piece.  An iron oxide over a raw umber looks pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let the piece dry and spray some protective acrylic coating and you end up with a pretty nice piece to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/painting-resin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Resin Painting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Print and Play the Royal Game of Ur</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/13/royal-game-or-ur-pnp/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/13/royal-game-or-ur-pnp</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Print and plays are a great way to try out games before investing money on a nice set.  In some cases, especially
with independent game designers, it’s the only way to play their games.  They are also great for classroom use or
group use.  If anything, it’s fun and cheap entertainment.  I recently explored creating one for the Royal Game of Ur
using pocket change for pieces and casting tokens. It was a fun experiment and for those interested, I was able to create the entire PDF (diagrams
and all) using Google Docs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur-pnp-preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur Print and Play&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur-pnp.pdf&quot;&gt;download the PDF&lt;/a&gt;, grab a pocket full of change and some friends to
re-live those college budget nights. :) Happy Gaming!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Senet</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/08/12/how-to-play-senet/"/>
   <updated>2017-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/08/12/how-to-play-senet</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Senet is an ancient Egyptian board game played on a 3x10 grid board.  It was being played before 3000 B.C. and have been
found in burial tombs.  One of the most eleaborate boards belonged to King Tutankhamun.  No rules have survived and many
game historians have sought to reconstruct the game.  These rules are by British Museum curator, Irving Finkel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/senet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Senet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 7 pieces and they are placed on the top half of the board alternating colors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After the board is setup, the first player takes 4 casting tokens and throws them to determine the value how much to
move their piece.  The value is determined by how many marked sides are up.  If no marked sides are showing the value is 5.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can only move forwards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can land on a vacant spot or swap places with an opponent’s piece if it’s &lt;em&gt;undefended&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have two pieces right next to each other on adjacent squares, they defend each other and therefore cannot be swapped.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you throw a 1, 4 or 5.  You get to throw again. 
 (All throws must be complete before moving pieces)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sum of multiple throws can be divided among several of your pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You cannot swap pieces that are on safe squares.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The last 5 squares are special:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Square 26&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square, must throw 5 to leave this space.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 27&lt;/strong&gt;: Water square, go back to the beginning of the board.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 28&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 29&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square, must throw 2 to leave this space.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Square 30&lt;/strong&gt;: Safe square, must throw 1 to leave this space.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player able to get all 7 of their pieces off the board wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Five Lines</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/31/how-to-play-five-lines/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/31/how-to-play-five-lines</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Five Lines was a game originating from Ancient Greece where it was known as Penta Grammai.  The earliest reference to it is in 600 B.C. in a verse by Greek poet, Alkaios.  It became popular among the Romans and boards have been found etched into
pavements of old Roman towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/five_lines.png&quot; alt=&quot;Five Liness&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 5 pieces and places them on their side of the board (one per line/rectangle).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player take turns rolling a single die and moves one of their pieces counterclockwise according to the die value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only 1 piece is allowed per line, so pieces are only allowed to move to a vacant spot.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The exception is the middle line (called the sacred line) is where more than 1 piece can land.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player must move a piece even if it means moving a piece off the sacred line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player is unable to move into a vacant spot or the sacred line, they pass.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player able to get all 5 of their pieces onto the sacred line of the opposing side wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Five Men's Morris</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/25/how-to-play-five-mens-morris/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/25/how-to-play-five-mens-morris</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Five Men’s Morris is a merels game from Europe.  It also almost identical to Six Men’s Morris which only differs
by the fact that each player gets an extra piece.  Diagrams of the board have been found in 16th century manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1-place-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/five.png&quot; alt=&quot;Five Men's Morris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 5 pieces and take turns placing them on the board with the intention of trying to make 3 in a row.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces should be placed on any place where there is an intersection of lines (corners included).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once all the pieces are placed, the first player moves one of its pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can move along a line to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a player forms a row of 3, they are to remove an opponent’s piece off the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capturing/Removing a piece that is part of a row of 3 is not allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A player loses when they are down to 2 pieces.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Three Men's Morris</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/20/how-to-play-three-mens-morris/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/20/how-to-play-three-mens-morris</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Three Men’s Morris is a simple strategy game played by the ancient Romans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-1-place-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 1: Place the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/three.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three Men's Morris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 3 pieces and take turns placing them on the board with the intention of trying to make 3 in a row.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces should be placed on any place where there is an intersection of lines (corners included).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-2-move-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Move the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once all the pieces are placed, the first player moves one of its pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can move along a line to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players take turns moving their pieces until someone gets three in a row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to make three in a row wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Roman Cats - A Retheming of Shut the Box</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/07/03/retheming-shut-the-box/"/>
   <updated>2017-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/07/03/retheming-shut-the-box</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Retheming is a fun way to breathe new life into old abstract games.  I recently experimented with making wooden Roman numeral dice and that is where the idea began.  Shut the Box is an old English pub game that is still fairly popular today.  There are many variations and sets available online.&lt;br /&gt;
I was thinking about how to make a set without having to construct the actual box.  It’s a super simple game that could be potentially played using just a deck of card and set of dice.  With this in mind, I made 9 cat tokens, each with a Roman numeral across the top.  My 11 year old nephew and his friend assisted me with the cat drawings.
 &lt;strong&gt;Roman Cats&lt;/strong&gt;, a kitty themed version of Shut the Box was born!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/roman-cats-finished.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roman Cats&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-play&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Play&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the 9 cat tokens in a row with the Roman numerals facing up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determine the first player&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 1st player starts by rolling the set of dice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The player takes any combination of available numbered tokens that add up to the
sum of the rolled dice.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For example, a player rolls a 4 and 5 (total 9). They may take any available tokens that add up to 9:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
 9  &lt;br /&gt;
 4, 5   &lt;br /&gt;
 1, 3, 5  &lt;br /&gt;
 1, 8&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After the first player takes the appropriate tokens, the 2nd player rolls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players alternate until no more tokens are left to take&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player rolls and is unable to take tokens, their turn is over (no rerolls)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the token with the number 1 is the only one remaining, players may use 1 die to roll&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The game ends with there are no more cat tokens, each player then adds up there score.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The player with the highest score wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Optional End Rules&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The player who takes the last token receives an extra 6 points&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the player who took the last token is winning by less than 6 points, the losing player has a chance to roll both dice again.  If they roll exactly a 6, they also receive 6 bonus points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Roman numerals added an additional learning element since you have to know your Roman numerals to play!  It might also be interesting to make a Chinese version with Kanji characters. In any event, retheming games is a great way to include family and friends in interacting via board games.  My nephew and his friend (who both happen to love cats) approved and enjoyed a game that they may have not otherwise played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know not everyone has the equipment to make custom wooden pieces.  The wood burning kit itself can be a sizable investment.  If you want to try the game out, feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/roman-cats-pnp.pdf&quot;&gt;download the print and play&lt;/a&gt; version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/roman-cats-pnp-preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Roman Cats Print and Play&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either cut out the cards or place coins to designate which cat number is taken.  With this print out and a set of dice, you’ll be ready to play.  Happy Gaming!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Games - Discover and Play 5 Famous Ancient Games</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/06/03/discover-and-play-review/"/>
   <updated>2017-06-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/06/03/discover-and-play-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the individual discovering the beauty of ancient games, &lt;strong&gt;Games - Discover and Play 5 Famous Ancient Games&lt;/strong&gt; by Irving Finkel 
is a great gentle introduction into that world.  It is originally a children’s activity book published by the British Museum.
It takes a child (and the child at heart) through 5 different ancient race games: Duodecim Scripta, Royal Game of Ur, Ancient Egyptian Senet, Pachisi,
&amp;amp; Snakes and Ladders.  At just 36 pages, it is filled with interesting history and great pictures of ancient gaming artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes this book unique is the inclusion of colorful fold-out boards, punch-out pieces and rules for each game.  So not only do you get a great historical introduction, but the opportunity to &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; play the games!
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-pachisi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pachisi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is definitely a nice aspect since most of these games are a bit hard to come by and it is a great way to
try out each game before investing in nicer sets.  The boards and the rules are really the gems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-senet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Senet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The punch-out pieces are not as compelling (Though to be fair, this is true for  almost any print and play game).  It would probably be better to use tokens or coins instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-punchout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punch out&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it’s still a book worth picking up.  At the time of this writing, I picked up the book on Amazon for $1.99 plus shipping.  The last time I looked, there were quite a few still available.  For a few dollars, it’s a steal for an evening of history and fun wrapped up in a compact book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5games-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Fox and Geese</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/17/how-to-play-fox-and-geese/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/17/how-to-play-fox-and-geese</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fox and Geese is a northern European hunt game played with 13 geese and 1 fox.  Its asymmetrical nature is similar to that of hnefatafl.  Some theorize there is a relationship between two.  Queen Victoria is said to also be a fan on this medieval game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup-the-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup the Board&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arrange the 13 geese  pieces on the board according to the following layout:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/fox-geese.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fox and Geese&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fox player may place their piece on any empty point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The geese starts the game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geese may move along any line going from point to point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fox also moves along lines like the geese.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fox capures a goose by jumping over it into a vacant spot (like checkers), as long as the jump is along a line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If possible, the fox is allowed to capture another goose if in a position to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geese can not capture the fox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The geese wins if the trap the fox so that it may no longer move.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The fox wins if it captures enough (10) geese so that it can’t be trapped.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a slight advantage to the geese so switching sides will balance out the game.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Nine Men's Morris</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/07/how-to-to-play-nine-mens-morris/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/07/how-to-to-play-nine-mens-morris</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nine Men’s Morris is an ancient game with an unknown origin.  Historic boards
have been found in Troy, Ireland, and Egypt.  The Romans took it across its empire and it has even found it’s way on the back of Viking Hnefatafl boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup-the-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup the Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/nine.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nine Men's Morris&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black starts the placement phase of the game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player gets 9 pieces and take turns placing them on the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces should be placed on any place where there is an intersection of lines (corners included).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Black starts the movement phase of the game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can move along a line to an adjacent point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a player has 3 of its own pieces in a row (called a mill), the player can then remove one of the opponent’s pieces from the board.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can not remove an opponent’s piece if it is part of a mill.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player is down to 3 pieces, they can move a piece to any vacant spot on the board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to capture all but 2 of the opponent pieces wins .&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a slight advantage to the first player so switching who starts
first will balance out the game.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Seega</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/03/how-to-play-seega/"/>
   <updated>2017-05-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/03/how-to-play-seega</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Seega is a small abstract game from 19th century Egypt.  It has some similarities with the tafl family of games with its sandwiching capture method.  It is
played on a 5x5 grid with 24 pieces (12 per player).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-setup-the-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Setup the Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/seega.png&quot; alt=&quot;Seega&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each player gets 12 pieces and take turns placing 2 pieces on the board, leaving the middle square empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The last player to place a piece starts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece can  move horizontally or vertically to an adjacent square (like a rook that can only move 1 space at a time).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces are allowed on the center square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a player is unable to move, the other player takes an extra turn to create an opening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piece is captured when a player is able to sandwich an opponent’s piece horizontally or vertically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capturing more than one piece with 1 move is possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving in between two enemy pieces is permitted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The center square is a safe place and a piece on it can’t be captured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to capture all the opponent pieces wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play the Royal Game of Ur</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/25/how-to-play-the-royal-game-of-ur/"/>
   <updated>2017-04-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/25/how-to-play-the-royal-game-of-ur</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Royal Game of Ur dates back to 2600 B.C.  It is the most complete ancient board game known to date. In 1926, Sir Leonard Woolley discovered the board and pieces while excavating the royal tombs in Ur (modern day Iraq).  British Museum’s curator Irving Finkel &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wHjznvH54Cw&quot;&gt;discovered the rules&lt;/a&gt; on a cuneiform tablet where both the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/collection_online/collection_object_details.aspx?objectId=8817&amp;amp;partId=1&quot;&gt;board and tablet are on display&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-start-with-a-blank-board&quot;&gt;Step 1: Start with a Blank Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur.png&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Game of Ur&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player receives 7 pieces and 3 casting tokens (can be sticks, coins, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The starting player casts their 3 tokens, count the value, and move a piece that many spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player 1 starts by entering a piece through the square marked with the letter ‘A’ and follow the path off the board to letter ‘B’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/royal-game-of-ur-path.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Path&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Player 2 follows a similar path but on their side.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you land a square occupied by the other player’s piece &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; it’s not on a marked square, the opponent’s piece is knocked off the board and must start over.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If a piece is on a marked square, it is safe from being knocked off.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you land a marked square, you can cast/roll again.  You don’t necessarily have to move that piece.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Once you made your way around the path, you must roll/cast the exact value to leave the board.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The first player to move all 7 of their pieces off the board wins.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play French Military Game</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/02/20/how-to-play-french-military-game/"/>
   <updated>2017-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/20/how-to-play-french-military-game</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The French Military Game is a 19th century game played with just 4 pieces: 3 hunters and 1 prey.
It was popular among French officers during the Franco-Prussian War of 1870-71.
Also known as Hare &amp;amp; Hounds, it is one of the smallest hunt games.  Mathematician Martin
Gardner, writer of monthly column “Mathematical Games” in Scientific American stated that
the game “combines extreme simplicity with extraordinary strategic subtley.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/french-military-game-layout1.png&quot; alt=&quot;French Military Game Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The hunter starts first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The hunter may move a piece one spot along a line to the right horizontally, diagonally or vertically.
(i.e. Hunters can’t move backwards).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The prey may move one step in any direction along a line (backwards or forwards).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hunters wins by trapping the prey so that it can no longer move.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Prey wins by passing all the hunters and reaching the other end of the board.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the hunter doesn’t advance to the right in 10 moves, the prey wins.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Fanorona</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/31/how-to-play-fanorona/"/>
   <updated>2016-12-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/31/how-to-play-fanorona</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fanorona is a game from Madagascar that dates back to 1680.  It is a beautiful game
played with 44 pieces (22 per player) and has a unique method of capturing.
The game has experienced a bit of a revival in modern times due to its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vn5WIwlYY6Y&quot;&gt;inclusion
in the Assassin’s Creed&lt;/a&gt; video game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/640px-Fanorona.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fanorona Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;White starts first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move from one point to another along a line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture by moving a piece directly towards a line of enemies (approach).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture by moving a piece away from a line of enemies (withdrawal).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove captured pieces immediately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player may continue to capture pieces via approach or withdrawal as long as
the enemies are on separate lines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Player must capture pieces if possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only one capture is allowed on a player’s first move.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Player wins by capturing all the opponents pieces.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fanorona is a really interesting game with a rich history.  Although a derivative of the Moorish
game alquerque, the unique capturing methods makes it stand solidly on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Sea Battle Tafl</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/11/06/how-to-play-sea-battle-tafl/"/>
   <updated>2016-11-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/06/how-to-play-sea-battle-tafl</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sea Battle Tafl is a modern variation of hnefatafl.  It is played on a 9x9 board with a total 25 of pieces much like &lt;a href=&quot;http://richgames.xyz/2016/09/25/how-to-play-tablut/&quot;&gt;Tablut&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/354px-Tablut_board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tablut Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cargo ship piece goes on the central square surrounded by defenders.  &lt;br /&gt;
The attacker/pirate ship pieces surround the defenders making a cross symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defenders start first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are no special squares.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the cargo ship leaves the central square anyone can occupy it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on 2 sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pirates capture the cargo ship by surrounding it on 4 sides.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cargo ship is without weapons and can’t aid in capturing pirates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can voluntarily enter a space between two enemies and not be captured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the cargo ship to an edge.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacking pirates wins by capturing the cargo ship.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Casting a Resin King</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/27/diy-resin-king/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/27/diy-resin-king</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the many enduring qualities of tafl games is the simplicity of the pieces.   No matter what size board or what rule variation (with perhaps the exception of &lt;a href=&quot;http://aagenielsen.dk/berserk_rules.php&quot;&gt;Berserk Hnefatafl&lt;/a&gt;), a set only need pieces of 3 distinctions: attackers, defenders and a king.  This makes it easier to create your own set.  It is common to see decorative glass gems as hnefatafl pieces.  In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.richgames.xyz/2016/10/24/diy-brandub/&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, we started to make a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.richgames.xyz/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/&quot;&gt;Basic Brandub&lt;/a&gt; game with these.  Let’s upgrade the set a bit with a hand-casted resin king piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tucked away in a drawer, I had an old chess pawn given to me by my best friend in grade school.  I’ve had this pawn since I was 7 or 8 years old.  It reminds me of my first friendship and being that tafl games are great to play with friends, it was a fitting piece to cast.  Obviously, pick an item that works for you and give your set a personal touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chess-pawn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chess Pawn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smooth-on.com/products/oomoo-30/&quot;&gt;silicone mold making kit&lt;/a&gt;, I carefully follow the instructions and made a mold of the chess pawn.  This stuff is messy and gooey, so be sure to wear gloves and cover the work area with newspapers.  The mold takes about 6 hours to cure, so be patient.  It took a few tries to get it right, but the result was a durable mold I can use over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many types of resin to choose from.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alumilite.com/store/p/934-Alumilite-White-Amazing-Casting-Resin.aspx&quot;&gt;Alumilite makes a fast curing, beginner friendly resin&lt;/a&gt; that works great for small pieces.  Like the mold making kit, it’s important to follow the instructions carefully and use gloves while casting the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 20 minutes, I had a perfect copy of my original chess pawn that makes a great king piece in the &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/&quot;&gt;Basic Brandub&lt;/a&gt; set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chess-pawn-cast.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chess Pawn Cast&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One game’s pawn is another game’s king. Such is life.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Do-It-Yourself: Make a Brandub Set</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/24/diy-brandub/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/24/diy-brandub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Making board games can be a fun, creative and sometimes frustrating adventure. There is something wonderful about playing a game with family and friends on something created by your own hands.  This is the first in a series of Do-It-Yourself blog articles on how to do just that and some of the lessons learned in the process. In this first article, we will describe the beginnings steps in making a &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/&quot;&gt;Basic Brandub&lt;/a&gt; set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-board&quot;&gt;The Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foundation of every board game is…well…the board.  Our Basic Brandub set uses an 8 inch square board.  Your best bet is to go to a local lumber supplier to purchase some plywood and get it cut down to that size.  There are also some online options.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.craftparts.com/&quot;&gt;Woodworks Ltd.&lt;/a&gt; sells individual &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.craftparts.com/plywood-square-cutouts-p-5093.html&quot;&gt;8x8 squares that are 1/8 inch&lt;/a&gt; thick for relatively cheap.  If you don’t mind spending a bit more, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kencraftcompany.com/&quot;&gt;KenCraft Company&lt;/a&gt; has a great selection of plywood and if you email them they will cut it down to the size you want for a fee.  Be warned you will be spending more on cutting fees and shipping than on the plywood itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the piece of plywood, sand it down to the desired smoothness.  Don’t skimp too much on this step.  The more time put into the sanding, the better the board will be.  Mark out the grid using 1 inch squares and a 1/2 inch border.  This will produce a 7x7 Brandub board where the gameplay happens on the squares (in oppose to the intersections).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a woodburning pen and a metal ruler, burn the lines in.  Unfortunately, the metal will draw heat from the woodburning pen and cause the lines to be a bit inconsistent in darkness.   Don’t dismay and just keep going.  When all the lines are done, carefully go over the lines again without the ruler to fill in any gaps.  Burn an ‘x’ into the corner and center squares.  Coat the board with a layer of sanding sealant, let it dry (about 1/2 hour) and smooth with #0000 steel wool (super fine grade).  Finally, finish with beeswax.  It is also possible to skip the sanding sealant and just use beeswax.  The surface won’t be as hard or smooth but the beeswax will produce a lovely finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pieces&quot;&gt;The Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brandub requires 13 pieces: 8 attackers, 4 defenders and 1 king.  This can
be easily accomplished with different colored glass gems. These are commonly
found in hobby stores for decorative purposes.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hobbylobby.com/&quot;&gt;Hobby Lobby&lt;/a&gt; is a great resource with a variety of colors and sizes.  The standard size (around 18mm) will fit the 1 inch squares pretty nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You now have a complete and playable Brandub set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diy-brandub-gems.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brandub&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for the next article and upgrade your set by casting a king piece in resin.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Fetlar Hnefatafl</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/12/how-to-play-fetlar-hnefatafl/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/12/how-to-play-fetlar-hnefatafl</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Fetlar rule variant is a common and popular way to play hnefatafl on a 11x11 board. There are 37 total pieces,
24 attackers, 12 defenders and 1 king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Hnefatafl_11x11_board.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Fetlar  Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The king piece goes on the central square surrounded by his defenders forming a diamond shape.
The attacker pieces surround the defenders along the perimeter of the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers start first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king piece can go to the corner squares or central square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other pieces can pass through the central square after the king leaves but can’t stop there (think freeway with no exit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on two sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture 3 pieces at most with 1 move.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture pieces against the central square and corner squares as though your piece is on it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The king is special, attackers needs to surround him on 4 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is next to the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 3 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the king to the corner square.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacker wins by capturing the king.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.  This is not really a step in the Fetlar rules as much as it’s a good chance to play both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A Review of The Lewis Chessmen Unmasked</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/07/lewis-chessmen-unmasked-review/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/07/lewis-chessmen-unmasked-review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Any fascination with the ancient game of hnefatafl will eventually lead to the Lewis Chessmen.  The most commercially available set, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tafl.cyningstan.com/stock/1242/the-viking-game&quot;&gt;The Viking Game&lt;/a&gt; uses pieces inspired by them. The more motivated enthusiast have used them in DIY sets and their Norse origin is undeniable.  There are a ton of books out there about the Lewis Chessmen. The British Museum and the National Museum of Scotland put on a joint exhibition (not all the pieces belong to one museum) in 2010. &lt;em&gt;The Lewis Chessmen: Unmasked&lt;/em&gt; by David Caldwell is the companion book to that exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/about_us/news_and_press/statements/the_lewis_chessmen.aspx&quot;&gt;The Lewis Chessmen&lt;/a&gt; is a collection of chess pieces dating back to the 12th century.  They were found accidentally in the
Isle of Lewis.  The book does a wonderful job of describing its mysterious discovery, its Scandanavian roots and theories about who they may have belonged to.  It’s a short (80 pages) companion book and catalogs each piece 
with beautiful photographs. Two of the pages are dedicated to connecting the chessmen to hnefatafl, suggesting that the kings doubled as pieces in both games.  There is evidence to support this notion as double-sided boards have been found at archaelogical sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is a great read and introduces these little figures in a compelling way.
Though it is a pale substitute for viewing the chessmen in real life, it does a pretty good job of fueling the intrigue. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/lewis-chessmen-unmasked.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lewis Chessmen Unmasked&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Tablut</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/25/how-to-play-tablut/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/25/how-to-play-tablut</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tablut is played on a 9x9 board with a total 25 of pieces.  This includes 16 attackers, 8 defenders and 1 king.
It was played in Lapland as late as the 18th century and is the most documented hnefatafl game thanks to Swedish botanist Carl Linneaus.  In 1732, while touring the area he came across the game played by the locals and &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/stream/ungdomsskrifter02linne#page/n155/mode/2up&quot;&gt;described it in his diary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/354px-Tablut_board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tablut Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The king piece goes on the central square surrounded by his defenders.
The attacker pieces surround the defenders making a cross symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers start first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king piece can go to the central square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the king leaves the central square, he can’t go back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other pieces can pass through the central square after the king leaves but can’t stop there (think freeway with no exit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on two sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can voluntarily enter a space between two enemies and not be captured.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture pieces against the central square as though your piece is on it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is in the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 4 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is next to the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 3 sides to capture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is anywhere else on the board he is captured like any other piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the king to an edge.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacker wins by capturing the king.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Play Brandub</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/how-to-play-brandub/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/20/how-to-play-brandub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Brandub is an Irish variant of hnefatafl.  It is played on a 7x7 board with 13 pieces.
Although it is the tiny sibling of all the hnefatafl games, it is just as fun and strategic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-arrange-the-pieces&quot;&gt;Step 1: Arrange the Pieces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrange the pieces on the board according to the following layout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/283px-Brandub_board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Brandub Layout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The king piece goes on the central square surrounded by his defenders.
The attacker pieces surround the defenders making a cross symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-learn-the-rules&quot;&gt;Step 2: Learn the Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attackers move first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces move like rooks in chess, horizontally and vertically as many spaces are there are available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not jump, skip, frolic, dance, fly or hop over other pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces can not move diagonally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only the king piece can go to the corner squares or central square.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the king leaves the central square, he can’t go back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other pieces can pass through the central square after the king leaves but can’t stop there (think freeway with no exit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capture pieces by surrounding the other player’s piece on two sides either horizontally or vertically (not diagonally).
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_normal_capture.png&quot; alt=&quot;Normal Capture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can voluntarily enter a space between two enemies and not be captured.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_volunteer.png&quot; alt=&quot;Voluntarily enter between two enemies&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can capture pieces against the central square and corner squares as though your piece is on it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is in the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 4 sides to capture.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_king_capture_4_sides.png&quot; alt=&quot;Capture on 4 sides&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is next to the central square, attackers needs to surround him on 3 sides to capture.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/120px-Tafl_king_capture_3_sides.png&quot; alt=&quot;Capture on 3 sides&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the king is anywhere else on the board he is captured like any other piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The defender wins by getting the king to the corner square.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The attacker wins by capturing the king.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-switch&quot;&gt;Step 3: Switch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first game switch sides and play again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, most people feel that it’s easier to win as the defender.  This is one of the characteristics of hnefatafl games due to it’s asymmetrical nature.  The strategies of an attacker is more long term.  Not to worry, as each player gets better the game becomes more balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is Hnefatafl?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/19/what-is-hnefatafl/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/19/what-is-hnefatafl</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Besides it’s somewhat unfortunate name, hnefatafl (pronounced “neffa-taffle”) is a wonderful ancient game the Vikings played.  Commonly thought
to be a predecessor of chess, it is much simpler but just as addicting.  Originally from
Scandanavia, as the Vikings migrated (a.k.a. raided other regions) they brought hnefatafl with
them, introducing it to the local people.
Different regions played slightly different variations of the game but the core fundamental strategy stayed the same.
The size of the board also varied depending on the local taste.  It’s kind of like how Chinese food is different but familiar no matter what country you’re in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defenders and their king always sit in the middle of the board, outnumbered by twice as many
attackers.  The board is always an odd number of squares (i.e. 7x7, 9x9, 11x11, etc.).  The defender’s 
objective is to get the king to the safety of a corner square (or edge depending on the hnefatafl version).
The attacker’s objective is to capture the king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of the board and the name of the game also varied depending on the region.  The Irish variant is called
“brandub” and is played on a 7x7 board.  The Norse version seemed to be commonly played on 11x11 or 13x13 board.  &lt;br /&gt;
Tablut from Lapland is played on 9x9 board.  Today, most commercially available hnefatafl sets are on a 11x11 board.
Each version contain it’s own characteristics but all belong to the tafl family of games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most obvious attributes of hnefatafl is it’s asymmetrical nature.  The fact that one player
gets just about twice as many pieces as the other &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; very strange and unfair.  But that is one 
the many enduring qualities of this game.  Playing different sides requires different ways of thinking.
The rules are simple and easy to learn, but the gameplay is complex and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hnefatafl, like other ancient games isn’t owned by any one person or company.  It’s the open source of the physical
gaming world.  This gives people the freedom to explore without the legal issues of proprietary games.  Take a look online and you’ll find a plethora of hand-made do-it-yourself as well as mobile and online versions.
Hnefatafl is not a game most people know about.  But it’s certainly a game that is experiencing a bit of revival.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Basic Brandub</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/09/18/basic-brandub/"/>
   <updated>2016-09-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/18/basic-brandub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/brandub-product.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brandub&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brandub is the Irish variant of the ancient Viking game of hnefatafl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This board is hand-made using 8 inch square plywood that is 3/8 inch thick.  The pattern is
burned into the wood using the pyrography technique. 
Included is a set of glass gems, 8 black attackers, 4 red defenders and
a hand-casted resin king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with many hand-made products, no two boards are alike.  There may be minor irregularities that gives
each set a unique rustic character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;WARNING: CHOKING HAZARD - This product contains small parts and is not suitable for children.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Available for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/listing/485250523/hnefatafl-brandub&quot;&gt;purchase&lt;/a&gt; on Etsy.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
